<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three questions resolved briefly and plainly, viz. What conceptions ought we to have of the blessed God? What are those truths, whereof the knowledge appeareth most indispensibly necessary unto our salvation; and (therefore) to be first and most learnt by us? What is the change wrought in a man by God's H. Word and spirit, before he can safely conclude himself pass'd from death to life? Being the summ of three sermons. By Daniel Burgess.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5718A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213037</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825563</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30289)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1755:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three questions resolved briefly and plainly, viz. What conceptions ought we to have of the blessed God? What are those truths, whereof the knowledge appeareth most indispensibly necessary unto our salvation; and (therefore) to be first and most learnt by us? What is the change wrought in a man by God's H. Word and spirit, before he can safely conclude himself pass'd from death to life? Being the summ of three sermons. By Daniel Burgess.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst at the Bible and Three Crowns, at the lower end of Cheapside, and Robert Gibbs at the Golden Ball in Chancery-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With three final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29947:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29947:1"/>
            <p>THREE QUESTIONS Reſolved briefly and plainly, <hi>VIZ.</hi> What Conceptions ought we to have of the bleſſed God? What are thoſe Truths, whereof the Knowledge appeareth moſt indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly neceſſary unto our Salvation; and (therefore) to be firſt and moſt Learnt by us? What is the Change wrought in a Man by God's H. Word and Spirit, before he can ſafely conclude himſelf paſs'd from Death to Life? Being the Summ of three Sermons. By <hi>Daniel Burgeſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>John 21.15.</bibl> 
               <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto him, Feed my Lambs (i. e.</hi> Souls, even the Loweſt.)</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 3.2.</bibl> 
               <hi>I have fed you with Milk, and not with Meat, (i. e.</hi> Doctrine fit for weaklings, not folk of ſtrong under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.)</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> and <hi>Robert Gibbs</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29947:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29947:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Congregation under my Care.</head>
            <p>IT is ſaid, my Brethren, that whatever Affections be in the Middle, they have two ſharp Ends.</p>
            <p>Our firſt Love has been as Zealous, as our firſt Knowledge was Wondrous. I am perſuaded alſo, that when we ſhall be Parted, it will be no leſs Ardent. And our ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be, as that of our Limbs from each other would be. May it be our Care, that, whiles we are Kept together by good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, we admit no chill in that ſweet and uſeful Grace; but ſhew it to be a godly Love, by having it like the Love of God, That is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable.</p>
            <p>I have nothing for you Great, but my Love. Next unto it, is my Labour: But, as my Talent is ſlender, that it ſelf is ſhorter than my Deſire. Without your very great Affection, I can expect little ſucceſs of my Preaching or Writing. Thereby I am encouraged unto both, and in both, as yet. It is that which hath given the <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:29947:3"/> unto theſe Notes. For, tho' of the Truths of God in them, I ſtudy to think moſt honourably: yet, as to any thing that is mine in them, I praiſe God, I do think very deſpicably. And am prepared to hear it undiſturbedly, if others ſhall think ſo too.</p>
            <p>Neither do I purpoſe to put you off with theſe Fragments. But pay the whole that I am Debtor of by Promiſe unto you, if the Lord will, and I live. I muſt beg your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience indeed for ſome time. Nor need I ſay for what Reaſons; being all that know me, know them alſo.</p>
            <p>You think, (as I do, tho' on a different reaſon,) my Days on Earth will be few. Be they more or leſs, the greateſt part of them ſhall be ſpent in Pains and Prayers for your Perſons and Families. While I am capable of either, You, more than any others, ſhall have them. Even Self-love bids you Pray for me: and I know you have other Motives. Therefore I Expect it, and not Intreat it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am, <hi>An Affectionate Servant of your Faith, Obedience and Joy,</hi> D. Burgeſs.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29947:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Q 1.</hi> What Conceptions ought we to have of God?</head>
            <p>OF all Truths, it is the moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that <hi>there is a God.</hi> And of all things Knowable, it is moſt neceſſary that we Know, what He is. This to Know perfectly, is impoſſible. An Oyſter-ſhell cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Ocean; nor a finite Mind com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend an infinite Object. 'Tis only God himſelf can fully Know himſelf. But, He made our Minds to Know Him, with a Knowledge ſufficient to ſerve and enjoy Him. Of this, we are Capable. For this, He vouchſafeth us means Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful. And without this, every Mother's Child muſt be everlaſtingly miſerable.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Thoughts</hi> of Him, are the Seed of all our <hi>Affections, Words,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> toward Him. I, and towards one another too. If theſe be corrupt, nothing is ſound, of all that is in us, or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29947:4"/> comes from us. Nor can theſe be Good, but when they are <hi>True,</hi> and agreeable unto their Rule; <hi>Powerful,</hi> and Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto their End. The Rule of them, is God's own Word; in the Books of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Scripture publiſhed.</p>
            <p>The End of them, is the <hi>Exaltation</hi> of God's Name, the <hi>Subjection</hi> of us to his Authority, the <hi>Actuation</hi> of us unto Obedience to his Law. When they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this Rule, and obtain this End, our <hi>Conceptions</hi> of God are what they ought to be.</p>
            <p>Indeed, <hi>Revelation is the Meaſure of Faith</hi> God requires, for Degree, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what He gives. He giveth ſome, an hundred-fold more advantages for Knowing Him, than he beſtoweth on others. And He will accept an hundred-fold leſs from ſome men, than others. Let Miniſters, Rich men, and ſuch as ſit under the beſt Miniſtry of the Word, remember this and tremble. Let the Unlearned, the Poor, and thoſe that live neceſſitouſly under the worſt Miniſtry, think of this, and in hope get all they are able.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, be it conſidered by all. We all have the <hi>great Volume</hi> of the World, that the Heathens had: and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29947:4"/> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> that the Jews had: and <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel-Light,</hi> that they had not. Yea, and ſuch <hi>Diſplays</hi> of it in <hi>England,</hi> as the very Churches beyond the Seas have not. [And I wiſh it better obſerved, what <hi>London</hi> has, that moſt Countrey parts are deſtitute of.] Much is given to <hi>England,</hi> very much to <hi>London.</hi> And the Thoughts of Himſelf that God will require from us <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> and ſpecially <hi>Londoners,</hi> muſt be preſumed to extend unto theſe ſixteen Particulars.</p>
            <p>Seven concerning his <hi>Eſſence.</hi> Three concerning his <hi>Relations, common</hi> unto all his Creatures. And ſix concerning his <hi>Relations ſpecial</hi> unto our ſelves. If any one ſeem Excuſable, I pray the Reader to give me his reaſon for that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. If all do ſeem Impoſſible to be gotten and held in Memory, I deſire that it be thought as true as I can make it appear, <hi>viz.</hi> that I find <hi>Children</hi> of ten years old, that can perfectly and pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly get and retain them in their Memories. And if <hi>grown people</hi> cannot ſo do, they muſt take what follows ſuch their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Mind. Read on, ye who have Will and Power.</p>
            <p>Concerning God's <hi>Eſſence</hi> or Nature;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29947:5"/> to wit, that by which He is what He is, and is differenced from all other things; it is to be born in Mind, that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncauſed, or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmade Being.</hi> A Creature is a thing contrived by God's Wiſdom, and made out of nothing by his Power; and this, freely, of his own Will and Choice. But God is a Being that never came out of Not-being. Was never Contrived by his own or any other Wiſdom. Never Made by his own or any other Power, and Will. For a thing to be the Cauſe of it ſelf, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by all the World to be Impoſſible. And for a Creature or ſecond Being to be the Cauſe of its God or firſt Being, is ſuch an abſurdity as no unbewitched Mind can ſwallow. That which is No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, can do nothing: If there was a time, when God was Nothing, ſurely at that time he could do Nothing. And if ſo; He could not make Himſelf. As for other Cauſes, I ask, as the Apoſtle in another caſe, <hi>Who hath firſt given to Him, and it ſhall be recompenſed?</hi> Rom. 35.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He is an Eternal Being.</hi> A Creature is a thing that has a Morn, a Noon, and a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29947:5"/> Night. A Beginning, Change, and End. An End, and a Return unto it's firſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingneſs, the firſt moment that God ceaſes to uphold it. Angels and our Souls, are of themſelves Mortal: 'Tis only by divine Will, Power and <hi>Suſtentation</hi> that they are Immortal, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. But God, is <hi>Je, Ho, Vah.</hi> A Being that Shall be, that Is, and that Hath ever been. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Beginning, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.2. Without Change, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.27. Without End, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.26.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndependent Being.</hi> A Creature, is a thing that cannot ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Material, Mix'd, and Spiritual Creatures all are weak, all as unable to <hi>Suſtain</hi> themſelves as to Produce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But God, is a Being that's above Depending. He came not into Being, by any Help, He continues not in Being by any. He Depends on nothing; that is, He depends not. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. He is <hi>El Shaddai,</hi> God All-ſufficient. So all, that He can need nothing: So all, that He can ſupport every thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>He is a Neceſſary Being.</hi> A Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is a thing that may, or may not, be. That muſt be, or muſt not be, as its
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29947:6"/> God pleaſeth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11. But God is a Being; that cannot but Be. One, to which 'tis eternally repugnant and impoſſible ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther never to have Been, or to ceaſe from Being. One who only hath Being, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily; and Immortality, neceſſarily. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. One whoſe Being and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, never coſt one act of his Will or Power! Nor are capable of being made to ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>He is an All-perfect Being.</hi> A Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a thing of Imperfection in every reference. One, that has more of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, than Thing, ſay the Schools. One, whoſe Perfection, ſuch as 'tis, is three-fold: Of Being, of Working, of Well-being. Every Creature is Imperfect in all: And after the day of Judgment, will in all be but Finite. Nor has any one Creature, the Perfections that divine Goodneſs hath diſpers'd among all. But God is a Being of excellent Perfection, and perfection in every Excellency. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one Conceivable, by Men, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. I, and whatever is by both Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable. God, is above the Bleſſing and Praiſe of both. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.5. He is Above all that He has Revealed Himſelf unto us to be: And more than unto us finite
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29947:6"/> things is Revealed, or poſſible to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed. [See, Children, your <hi>Larger Catechiſm.</hi> See, others, Mr. <hi>Charnock</hi> of the Divine Attributes.] God's infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Mind cannot conceive, what He ſhould be better or greater than He is. And finite Minds muſt needs conclude, He is infinitely above all that they can conceive.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>He is a Tri-une Being.</hi> Or, a Being that ſubſiſts in three diſtinct Perſons. Here is the Myſtery of Myſteries. The hardeſt to be Underſtood; but eaſy, as any, to be Believed. With ſuch a Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs 'tis reveal'd in the bleſſed Goſpel. How neceſſary it is to be Believed, is hence evident: To wit, that (1.) This manner of Being is the <hi>Top-moſt</hi> glory of God. It is the beſt manner of Being, that can be. That without which, 'tis hard to think how God ſhould be in Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf glorious infinitely, or bleſſed infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. His Creatures are, and can be, but finite. And what can they ſpeak infinite! The Infinite glory of the divine Perſons, ſhines in their Relations one to the other. I, and their Bleſſedneſs conſiſteth in their Loving, and being Loved of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. [Dr. <hi>Cheynel</hi> of the Trin. ch. 5th.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29947:7"/> deſerves good reading.] (2.) The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of God's ſubſiſting in, or being Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Spirit, diſtinctly; is moſt firmly <hi>connected</hi> with all the parts of our Chriſtian Religion: And ſo, that if Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or Unbelief of the glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity prevail on us, our Chriſtianity is loſt. And 'tis another Goſpel, even a high Road to Sin and Hell that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take us unto. See <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>John</hi> 14.26. <hi>John</hi> 15.26. A <hi>Tree,</hi> is one. Its <hi>Root, Trunk,</hi> and <hi>Branch,</hi> are three. Have three Manners of Being: the Root is of it ſelf; the Trunk is of the Root; the Branches are from both Root and Trunk. They give forth Fruit, in a threefold manner: the Root, <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> and firſtly; the Trunk <hi>continuedly,</hi> and ſecondly; the Branch <hi>compleatly</hi> and immediately. Who cannot apply this? God is one. This one God, is <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> three Perſons. The <hi>Father</hi> is of Himſelf. The <hi>Son</hi> is of the Father. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is of the Father and Son. In the Communication of good, they all work joyntly, yet there are diſtinct Perſonal operations, by which they make way for the glory of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. <hi>Inchoation</hi> or Beginning of good, is from the Father; <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> is by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29947:7"/> Son; <hi>Conſummation,</hi> or compleating, is by the Spirit. I do not forget, and I would have my Reader remember, St. <hi>Hilarie</hi>'s often quoted ſaying; <hi>viz.</hi> All Compariſons, though Helpful, are yet diſproportionable. 'Tis very true; no Similitude can reach the <hi>thing,</hi> but this, and others like it, may help our <hi>underſtandings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>He is the All-working Being.</hi> That Fore-ordains whatever cometh to paſs, and Effecteth whatever he Fore-ordains. To wit, in Works of Creation and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. A Creature is a thing that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not it ſelf come (that infinite ſpace,) from Nothing into Being. Cannot, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, uphold its Being, Virtues, Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Cannot govern it ſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. Cannot be undepending in reſpect of Working, any more than in reſpect of Being. But God is a Being, All-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. His Word ſpeaks all into <hi>Being:</hi> His Conſerving influence goes to our <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation:</hi> His Aſſiſting influence to our <hi>Operation.</hi> This his Aſſiſting influence or concurrence fore-goeth the <hi>Operation</hi> of Creatures. Fore-goes it in Order, though not in Time. It is Co-operation, or Co-working with the Creature. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29947:8"/> the Creature's <hi>Operation,</hi> God will not produce many Effects: And without God's <hi>Co-operation,</hi> the Creature can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not produce any. God's Co-working, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Immediate. With Immediateneſs of Virtue and Power; without which there could be no Effect: And with Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateneſs of Preſence too; for God is every where. He is called <hi>Hamakom,</hi> the Place. Laſtly, it is determining. There can be but one abſolute Determiner and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruler of <hi>Operations.</hi> And who is He, but God? And, if by Him, the <hi>Operations</hi> of Creatures were not abſolutely Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it would be very poſſible that He might be Fruſtrated, and Diſappointed of his Ends ſometimes. But there is nothing more impoſſible than that. Be it Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Though in the ſenſe fore-ſaid, God Worketh all; yet ſo, ſo Worketh He, that he Changes not the Nature of things, Offers no violence to them, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers them to act by and under him; and that as Freely, as though there were no <hi>Decree</hi> upon them, or <hi>Hand</hi> over-ruling them. [See Mr. <hi>Norton</hi>'s Orthod. Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt.]</p>
            <p>Concerning God's <hi>Relations common</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all his Creatures, let it be attended that follows in few words.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29947:8"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He is the Supream Benefactor.</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can be but the Bearers of his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits unto us. And of but ſome of 'em; and that but of the Out-parts of them too. The Benefactor is God. All-good we ever Have had, Have, and Shall ever have, God <hi>Contriveth, Willeth, Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</hi> He Begins all, Carries on all, Compleats all; Freely, without <hi>Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> Graciouſly, without <hi>Merit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He is the Supream Ruler.</hi> Creatures, have no Power or Authority but <hi>from</hi> Him, and <hi>under</hi> Him, and <hi>for</hi> Him His infinite Perfections, make him moſt Fit to rule. His Creation and Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things, give Him infinite Right and Title to rule all. To make Laws; to Judge according to them; to Execute Judgment ſo paſs'd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He is the Abſolute Proprietor, and Owner.</hi> Creatures are things that are not their Own, or one another's, any farther than, under Himſelf, God makes them ſo. God, is entirely his Own. And his Own, be all the Works of his hands. And without the ſhadow of a ſpot on his Juſtice, He may do what He will with his Own: Whether it be a Perſon, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29947:9"/> Kingdom, Church, World. His <hi>Authority</hi> can no more be Diſprov'd, than his <hi>Power</hi> be Reſiſted, if He ſet to Exalt, or Debaſe, or Deſtroy. I, and this without giving any account of his Matters.</p>
            <p>Concerning God's <hi>Relations ſpecial</hi> and particular unto our ſelves, be it conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 'Tis of importance, as great, as true; and as plain, as 'tis great, that every Soul come as near as may be to a full and juſt Concluſion concerning theſe; [Con, O my Friends, Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of Self-knowledge!] I appeal to my Readers, how needful it is that theſe ſix things be ever in our deepeſt and ſevereſt thoughts. That every of us get able to ſay, and keep ſaying concerning God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He is my Quondam-Friend and Father, even Immediate.</hi> He that before Sin's En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, dearly Loved and was Beloved by me. And that without a <hi>Mediator,</hi> Sacrificing and Interceeding for me. 'Tis He, that made me in his Likeneſs Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; an <hi>Intelligent</hi> and <hi>Immortal</hi> Being. And in his Likeneſs Moral; for Holineſs, Bleſſedneſs, and Dominion over inferior Creatures. 'Tis He, that entred Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29947:9"/> with me in my firſt Parent. A Covenant, to <hi>ſweeten</hi> his Government, and to <hi>ſecure</hi> my Obedience. A Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, of Terms unexceptionable. Yea, and founded not only in his Will, but in the very Nature of things themſelves. For it bound me, but to be bleſſed; that is, to be Holy. And threatned no evil at all, unleſs I firſt committed the worſt of all; that is, Sin. A Covenant alſo, ſign'd and ſeal'd with <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Such appear the Trees of Knowledge and Life to have been.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He is next my angry and armed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and in all appearance <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreconcileable.</hi> 'Tis He, that as ſoon as I ſinned, in <hi>Adam,</hi> loathed me, and my Soul alſo abhorred Him. He it is, that then took away his H. Spirit from me, and gave me up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bondage of the <hi>Law,</hi> that I had broken. To the Servitude of the <hi>Sin,</hi> that I had committed. To the Tyranny of <hi>Satan,</hi> to whom I had hearkened. To the Power of <hi>Death,</hi> that I had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. O the Wrath! oh the Vengeance! And alas! what Hope appear'd to Men, or to Angels, of any Reconciliation? Neither could imagine a Reconcilement to be <hi>Poſſible;</hi> and much leſs think it <hi>Future,</hi> or Coming.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:29947:10"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He is my Propitiated God, reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and inviting me to Reconciliation.</hi> Come ſeize me O Wonder and Joy! 'Tis He, that did not ſo for faln Angels; but for faln Men, gave his Co-eſſential Eternal Son for a Sin-offering. An Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>ſatisfying</hi> for all Iniquity, and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting</hi> every Mercy. And that ſo fully, that now upon the account hereof, I have <hi>Leave, Commandment,</hi> and <hi>Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to Seek, Pray, and Wait for the beſt, and all good things. Without Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and without Price; without any Quality or Work of my own, Satisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Deſerving. I, 'tis He, that by his <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> doth even ſtoop to Intreat, and Pray, and Beſeech me, to be friends with Him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. 'Tis He, that hath made it now the worſt of ſins, that I am capable of ſinning; to Preſume that I am a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate; and that there is no hope for my Recovery out of my Sin and Miſery, by his Grace in Chriſt unto All offered, without Exception.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>He is, as ſure as I Repent and Believe, my Reconciled God.</hi> He it is, that Layeth aſide all his Anger; Loveth freely; Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons fully; Accepts graciouſly my Soul,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29947:10"/> ſaying, <hi>All that I have is thine, Luk.</hi> 15. and <hi>I will be thy God:</hi> And all this in the firſt inſtant, wherein I Mourn for, and Turn from my Sin, ſo as to Believe on his Son. That is, to reſign up my ſelf to be Taught, Saved, and Ruled by Him. He it is that then turns from all his <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Wrath:</hi> yea, and when I Live up unto the Grace by me received, turns from all his very <hi>Paternal</hi> or <hi>Fatherly Diſpleaſure.</hi> He it is that leſſens his Love of <hi>Complacence</hi> in me, and <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of me, for none but Wilful and Preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sins. Sparing me for ſins of invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible infirmity and incurſion, as a Father doth the Son that deſires to ſerve him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>He, as ſure as He is my Reconciled, is my Covenanted God alſo.</hi> He never dealt with Man, in other way than this moſt ſweet one, of Covenant! <hi>Hallowed be his Name,</hi> He did not. And He it is, that now hath as well bound Himſelf to be my God, as me to be his Servant. He it is, that to my wondrous advantages hath thus Covenanted with me. (1.) He hath Covenanted with me <hi>Doubly.</hi> Firſt, in my Parents; promiſing me Mercy for their ſakes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. Promiſing them Mercy for me, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.6. Secondly, in my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29947:11"/> Perſon. He hath made a Covenant with me, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. (2.) He Covenanted with me <hi>Sacramentally;</hi> or Signedly and Sealedly. For Sacraments are Signs and Seals on God's part, Bonds and Badges on our parts, [as I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſhewn.] <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 20.16. Bleſs his Name, O my Soul! He hath Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly covenanted with thee in H. Baptiſm, and at his H. Table, and moſt Senſibly. (3.) He hath Covenanted with me, as not Nakedly but with Signs and Seals, ſo not Tardily, but (to my great benefit,) <hi>Early.</hi> Early, in my very Infancy. Before I could Commit an Actual ſin; ſo ſetting forth my Original ſin. Before I could Deſire Grace; ſo ſhewing abroad the Freeneſs of his Grace. So Early was I Baptized, and encouraged and engaged to Obey the Goſpel, when I came to years of capacity, that I cannot but ſee God's Kindneſs in foreſtalling Satan's Seducements. And all days of my Life, I will remember it, as <hi>David</hi> doth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.10. <hi>Thou art my God,</hi> [that is, my Covenant-God] <hi>from my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's belly, v.</hi> 9. <hi>Thou didſt make me to Hope when I was on my Mother's breaſts:</hi> [That is, Thou didſt even then, by the Covenant then ſign'd and ſeal'd unto me, lay in grounds and motives for my Hope
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29947:11"/> in Thee, when I ſhould come to years of underſtanding.] (4.) He hath ſign'd and ſeal'd Covenant with me <hi>Frequently.</hi> I am no ſtranger at his Table. His holy Bread many a time have I eaten. Times numberleſs, He hath cheared me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>He is my God, Oppignorated; or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to me by Pawns and Pledges.</hi> Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are much: Signs and Seals be wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Appendages</hi> to Divine Promiſes. But, behold here are alſo unexpreſſibly rich <hi>Pawns</hi> ſuperadded! God is He, that hath given me the higheſt, and moſt ſolemn, and ſweeteſt Teſtifications of his Will to be for ever my God, and Portion. The Earneſt of his Spirit, with his bleſſed Graces and Conſolations, enſure all the good things of the Covenant. They are ſuch <hi>Firſt-fruits,</hi> as make the beſt ſecurity for the whole <hi>Harveſt.</hi> And theſe hath Grace made mine.</p>
            <p>And now I beg Pardon in my Saviour's Blood, for all the Defects of this Paper. They whoſe <hi>Intreaties, Letters,</hi> and <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> have extorted it, are both to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Accept it. Let them, with me, ever remember this ſaying of the great
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29947:12"/> Light of our Age; <hi>The Sun may more eaſily be included in a ſpark of Fire, than the infinite Perfections of God be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in a finite Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:29947:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Q. 2.</hi> What are thoſe Truths, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Knowledge appeareth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> indiſpenſibly neceſſary unto our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vation? and in the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſirable?</head>
            <p>ALL ſober Chriſtians do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome Truths there be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt needs <hi>Know,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ever, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.11. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Truths there be, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> unto our <hi>Comfort</hi> in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> unto others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> out our Salvation: tho' the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> them be not abſolutely neceſſary working out the ſame.</p>
            <p>It ſeems not the Mind of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us Know, <hi>which</hi> the former ſort of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are in particular. And <hi>how Many</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there be. Nor can it be ſaid, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Uncertainty about them, is of diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage unto us. For, what if we were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo certain which they were? Being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> capacity of getting Knowledge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29947:13"/> ſort of Truths, it would be inconſiſtent with both <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> to take up content with the Knowledge of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer only.</p>
            <p>Sufficient it is for our <hi>Duty, Safety,</hi> and <hi>Comfort,</hi> to Know what thoſe Truths be; which, conſidering our Condition and Capacity, we are concerned <hi>firſt of all</hi> to Acquaint us with. And thoſe, which afterward our Intereſt obliges us, <hi>above all others,</hi> to get Informed of. 'Tis enough for us to Know, what are the <hi>Eſſential</hi> and <hi>Integral</hi> Doctrines, which made and enrich'd the Chriſtians which are gone to Heaven before us: and the right Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of which, will certainly make us <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Rich</hi> ones. God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in his Word, what theſe are. And from his H. Word, and agreeably unto it, I aſſay to declare what they are. With that <hi>plainneſs,</hi> which weak Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and that <hi>compendiouſneſs,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm Memories, do require at my hands.</p>
            <p>Be it premiſed, Sanctification is Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>begun;</hi> Salvation is Sanctification <hi>perfected.</hi> Grace and Glory differ but in degree. What is neceſſary to the one, is ſo unto the other. Now Sanctification is our <hi>Conformity</hi> unto God thro' Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And this is made by <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29947:13"/> By the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other; which is called <hi>all our Salvation and all our Deſire.</hi> Thoſe Truths there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which do moſt directly lead unto the ſame, and that acquaint us with it, and ſhew us the uſe of it, are of the <hi>greateſt weight and importance:</hi> and are to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto in the <hi>firſt place.</hi> It hath not been without ſome ſucceſs, that I have commended to be firſt learned (before any Catechiſm it ſelf) theſe <hi>ſeven</hi> Articles.</p>
            <p>A. 1. God, the Father, Son, and Spirit, created the World. He created Man, Wiſe, Holy, Bleſſed, and Honourable. He Covenanted with the <hi>firſt Man,</hi> and with his <hi>Poſterity</hi> in him; that, if they Obey'd perfectly, they ſhould be for ever Happy, if they Sinned, they ſhould Die. This is called the <hi>Covenant of Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 2. <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt Man, and his <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity</hi> in him, brake that Covenant, and thereby fell under God's wrath and curſe, and Sin and Satan's power. Note this Breach of Covenant.</p>
            <p>A. 3. God, the Father did, from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Covenant with his Son Jeſus Chriſt, for the <hi>Redemption</hi> of Sinners from Sin and Miſery: to wit, by his being made <hi>Man,</hi> and a <hi>Servant,</hi> and a <hi>Curſe</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward an <hi>Interceſſor</hi> for them. This is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29947:14"/> named the <hi>Redemption-Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 4. In purſuance of this Redemption-Covenant, when Man had ſinned, Chriſt the Saviour was Preached. And in Him, Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption <hi>offered:</hi> with Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Faith in God thro' Him, and New Obedience <hi>required.</hi> This is called the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 5. For our <hi>Encouragement</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God's <hi>Promiſes</hi> made unto us in the Covenant of Grace; and for our farther <hi>Engagement</hi> to fulfil the <hi>Demands</hi> from us in it; God always pleaſed to order this Covenant to be ſolemniſed, by ſome outward <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of his own appointment. And his Ceremonies appointed for theſe ends, in the <hi>New-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi>-Church, are <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> Theſe are call'd therefore, the <hi>Signs and Seals of the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 6. Obedience unto the Goſpel, in the <hi>Faith</hi> of Chriſt, and by the Help of the Holy Ghoſt, is of neceſſity unto all that have <hi>inwardly conſented</hi> unto the Covenant of Grace; and that have had it <hi>outwardly ſolemniſed</hi> betwixt God and them, in Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>A. 7. Beſides leſſer <hi>Rewards</hi> in this life to thoſe that Enter and Keep the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb facs="tcp:29947:14"/> of Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on thoſe that En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hath ſet a day wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Bodies of all men out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> unite them to their Souls: and, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nity, will Reward the former, and Puniſh the latter, in Soul and Body.</p>
            <p>In an <hi>Hour's</hi> time, an attentive Mind of ordinary capacity, will Ken theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. If but happily opened by a skilful Teacher. [Yet contain they much more, than multitudes of our people underſtand at forty and <hi>fifty years</hi> of age. Be <hi>aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, oh Heavens!</hi>] I judge them the moſt apt for Explication and Inculcation on firſt Beginners, whether Children or Grown People.</p>
            <p>Being competently acquainted with this <hi>ſhorteſt Summary,</hi> that which I would next commend, followeth in theſe, not many, but orderly Poſitions.</p>
            <p>P. 1. The <hi>Rule,</hi> and the <hi>Object</hi> of ſaving Truth is moſt Conſiderable by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirers after Truth.</p>
            <p>P. 2. The <hi>Rule</hi> is, the Old and New <hi>Teſtament</hi> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Penned by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Whereof th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Sufficiency</hi> are certain.</p>
            <p>P. 3. The Object is He whoſe name
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29947:15"/> JAM. Glorious, above all Bleſſing and Praiſe, for his <hi>Eſſence,</hi> which is One: <hi>Subſiſtence,</hi> which is in Three diſtinct Perſons: <hi>Works,</hi> which are inward, and outward. [Of Eſſence and Subſiſtence ſee before, <hi>p.</hi>]</p>
            <p>P. 4. The Outward Works of God are of <hi>Creation,</hi> and <hi>Providence.</hi> One is God's giving firſt Being unto all things. The other, is his preſerving and ordering them unto his own wiſe and holy End.</p>
            <p>P. 5. God's <hi>General</hi> Providence, is over all things. His <hi>Principal,</hi> is over Men and Angels.</p>
            <p>P. 6. God's Providence over Man, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects man's fourfold Eſtate: to wit, of <hi>Innocence,</hi> of <hi>Miſery,</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and of <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 7. Of Grace toward man, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable are the <hi>Fountains,</hi> Election and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. The <hi>Veſſels,</hi> God's Church and People. The <hi>Degrees,</hi> Vocation, Juſtification, Sanctification. The <hi>Means,</hi> Word, Sacraments, and Prayer.</p>
            <p>P. 8. Of Glory conferred by God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Children, obſervable are the four ſteps. <hi>In Aſſurance</hi> of eternal Love ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; <hi>in the Heavenly Manſions</hi> poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the day of Death to the day of Judgment; <hi>in the Honour put on at the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29947:15"/> day of Judgment; in the complete Glory</hi> beſtown after the day of general Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for ever to endure.</p>
            <p>Trial will beſt diſcover with how ſmall pains, and great Profit, this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium</hi> may begotten. And when got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it is by Underſtanding and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I adviſe that that which follows in <hi>twelve particulars,</hi> be ſtudyed. Namely, three concerning GOD, three concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing MAN, three concerning CHRIST, three concerning the APPLICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION of Chriſt that is ſaving unto us.</p>
            <p>P. 1. There is one only God, an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, Perfect, and Spiritual Eſſence.</p>
            <p>P. 2. This one God, is Father, Son, and Spirit. Diſtinguiſhed into three man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Subſiſtence, after a way incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible. The Father eternally <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting,</hi> the Son <hi>Begotten,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt <hi>Proceeding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 3. This one God is the <hi>Maker, Preſerver, Governour</hi> of all things, by infinite Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>P. 4. Man was made of <hi>ſuch a Body and Soul,</hi> that he was able to have attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>himſelf</hi> and his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, which was provided for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward if he had ſtood obedient.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29947:16"/>
            <p>P. 5. Man thus made, was <hi>Envyed</hi> and <hi>Tempted</hi> by the Devil, and <hi>Yielded</hi> wilfully unto his temptation, and brake the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> of God, and made himſelf and all his poſterity <hi>curſed</hi> by God, and <hi>envaſſalled</hi> to Sin and Satan; and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to eſcape the threatned Death.</p>
            <p>P. 6. Man thus immiſerated, was <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied</hi> by God. Who (in proſecution of an eternal Counſel and Covenant of peace) <hi>provided, preached,</hi> and <hi>offered</hi> a Saviour to him: even Jeſus Chriſt the righteous.</p>
            <p>P. 7. Jeſus Chriſt, this Saviour, is, as to his <hi>Natures,</hi> perfect God and perfect Man, in one Perſon: and, as to his <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> he is both Prophet, Prieſt and King; in both his <hi>ſtates,</hi> of Humiliation, and Exaltation.</p>
            <p>P. 8. Jeſus Chriſt's <hi>Humiliation</hi> in being made under the Law, Obeying the Precepts, and Suffering the Curſe of it, was <hi>deeper</hi> than was poſſible for any meer creature to undergo. And his <hi>Exaltation,</hi> in Riſing from the Dead as He did, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending up into Heaven, and Having all Power in Heaven and Earth given unto Him, was <hi>higher</hi> than any meer creature could poſſibly be exalted unto.</p>
            <p>P. 9. Jeſus Chriſt, being ſo Exalted, is <hi>Able</hi> to ſave to the uttermoſt, and <hi>Willing</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29947:16"/> to ſave Sinners the chiefeſt; <hi>welcomes</hi> all that penitently come unto Him, and <hi>mourns</hi> over all that obſtinately keep away from Him.</p>
            <p>P. 10. Application of Chriſt, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails unto our Salvation by Him, is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as is <hi>made by God,</hi> and ſuch as is <hi>made by our ſelves.</hi> God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies Chriſt to us by his <hi>H. Spirit,</hi> when by him he doth give us will and power to embrace him as offer'd in the Goſpel. We apply Chriſt unto our ſelves, when <hi>by Faith in-worked in us,</hi> we do embrace him as Prophet, Prieſt, and King, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting with Him, as ſuch, for ever.</p>
            <p>P. 11. Application of Chriſt ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, is that which every Soul ſhould <hi>ſeek, pray,</hi> and <hi>wait for,</hi> in the uſe of all God's Means appointed. Reſting not quietly, without ſome <hi>well-built Hopes</hi> that they have thro' grace attain'd it.</p>
            <p>P. 12. Application of Chriſt ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, no man <hi>may hope</hi> for, out of the Means by God appointed: but in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and diligent uſe of thoſe Means, no man <hi>need fear</hi> but he ſhall find it.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Novices</hi> have gotten thus far, they are more than a little advantaged to learn any of our <hi>Catechiſms.</hi> The <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> Aſſemblies, with bleſſed Mr. <hi>Lyes</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29947:17"/> moſt uſeful <hi>Expoſition;</hi> or any other. Yet (for Reaſons nameleſs) let me ſay, I would not have that, or any other, <hi>ſingly</hi> addreſs'd to.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Methods,</hi> are imperfect; ſaith our great Methodiſt. But he ſticks not to ſay, (What my heart thinks,) that the <hi>Creed, Lord's Prayer, Ten Commands,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine of the Sacraments,</hi> make the compleateſt body of Truths, that we can form. The Rule of <hi>Faith,</hi> is in the firſt: the Rule of our <hi>Prayers,</hi> in the ſecond: the Rule of our <hi>Practice,</hi> in the third: the great <hi>Encouragement</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi> to Believe, Pray, and Live holily, is ſet forth in the fourth. I conclude therefore with ſuch as ſmall a <hi>Map</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> of Truths in theſe, as ſome candid Hearers have not thought <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſeful.</hi> In number <hi>thirty ſeven.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Creed Truths <hi>twelve.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. There is a <hi>God</hi> that is three diſtinct Perſons, whoſe <hi>Revelations</hi> of himſelf are to be Credited; his <hi>Promiſes</hi> to be Relied on; his <hi>Demands</hi> from us Conſented unto hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and practically. And the Firſt Perſon of theſe three, [Firſt in <hi>Order,</hi> tho' not in <hi>Time,</hi> of Being and Working,] is named the <hi>Father.</hi> Father of All things by <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> of his Church by <hi>Adoption;</hi> of his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29947:17"/> Chriſt, by <hi>Generation</hi> in time, as he was Man; and by <hi>Generation eternal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable,</hi> as He is God. Father <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,</hi> as to <hi>Right</hi> to do whatever He plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and as to <hi>Strength</hi> wherewith to do it. And <hi>Maker of Heaven and Earth,</hi> that is, of all things. Of the Univerſity of Beings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Second Perſon of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, is, as to Office, <hi>Jeſus;</hi> a Saviour from Sin, by <hi>Price,</hi> by <hi>Prayer,</hi> and by <hi>Power.</hi> As to his Authority, He is <hi>Chriſt;</hi> ſet apart by God, Qualified, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned to be a ſaving <hi>Prophet, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>King.</hi> As to his Eſſence and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God the Father, He is <hi>His Only Son;</hi> to wit, by <hi>Eternal, Natural, Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable</hi> generation. As to His Supremacy and Honour, He is <hi>our Lord;</hi> to wit, by <hi>Natural</hi> right, as He is God; and by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated</hi> right, as he is the Lord to whom all Dominion is given, upon a double conſideration. That is, of the <hi>Price</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with He bought it from God: and of the <hi>Victory</hi> whereby He gain'd it all from Creatures.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Chriſt, as Man, was without <hi>humane</hi> Father. <hi>Conceived,</hi> that is, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, <hi>by the H. Ghoſt;</hi> who, firſt extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſanctified a portion of the Virgin-Mother's Fleſh and Blood, and then Made
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29947:18"/> thereof his <hi>ſinleſs</hi> Body. <hi>Born</hi> He was <hi>of that Virgin Mary,</hi> according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Mary,</hi> a Princeſs, by Extraction from King <hi>David,</hi> and Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> tho', of condition poor, and eſpouſed to a mean Artificer: <hi>Mary,</hi> an holy creature and humble. Yet, never called <hi>Mother</hi> by our Saviour Himſelf: nor ever made a <hi>Goddeſs</hi> by his Order.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Chriſt <hi>Suffered,</hi> from God, Men, and Devils, in Soul, Body, Rayment, Name, and Friends. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Pontius Pilate,</hi> that is, in the Time of his Preſidency un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Tiberius Caeſar. Was Crucified;</hi> a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of death by the <hi>Romans</hi> uſed, and by God eſpecially Curſed. <hi>Dead, Buried,</hi> and <hi>Deſcended into Hell;</hi> that is, His Soul and Body were ſeparated <hi>from each other,</hi> tho' neither of them were ſeparated <hi>from the Godhead</hi> at all. His Body, agreeably to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, but contrary to the <hi>Roman,</hi> was, the ſame day, <hi>Buried.</hi> And for part of three days, about <hi>thirty eight</hi> or <hi>forty hours,</hi> it abode apart from his Soul.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The third day</hi> (after his Death) <hi>He roſe again from the Dead.</hi> By his <hi>Father</hi>'s power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. By <hi>his own</hi> power, <hi>John</hi> 2.19. by the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi>'s power, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. By the <hi>One</hi> power of all the Divine Perſons. Elſe, He could
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29947:18"/> not have ſaved one Soul, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.13, 14.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This Chriſt, forty days after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, <hi>Aſcended into Heaven,</hi> (as <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> his Types fore-ſhewed.) And this in the view of his Diſciples<note n="*" place="margin">A Jury of Witneſſes.</note>. He <hi>ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Almighty;</hi> that is, He becomes next to God in Dignity, Power, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And under God, doth Adminiſter all things. Sitting, notes <hi>Security, Reſt,</hi> and honourable <hi>Dominion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. This Chriſt ſhall <hi>thence come to Judge the Quick and the Dead:</hi> All, alive at the Laſt day: and all, before that time Dead. True, God as God, in that day, is Judge <hi>Supreme.</hi> Chriſt Mediator, is Judge <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legate</hi> and <hi>Conſtitute,</hi> that pronounceth Sentence. And his very Saints are Judges by <hi>Aſſeſſion</hi> and <hi>Approbation</hi> of his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. It muſt not be forgot, that He judgeth <hi>every of us</hi> when we Die. Tho' not <hi>all of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> together; nor with Execution of all his Judgment upon our Souls and Bodies, till the Laſt day.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The third Perſon of the Godhead is named <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Ghoſt. Ghoſt</hi> ſignifies Breath or Spirit. This glorious Perſon, bears this name with a <hi>ſpecialty;</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eternally and inconceivably <hi>Spirated</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:29947:19"/> or <hi>Breathed</hi> forth from the Father and Son. And is in like ſort ſtyled <hi>Holy;</hi> as being by Office the Worker of all <hi>renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Holineſs</hi> in fallen Man.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This, Father, Son, and Spirit, have an <hi>Holy, Catholick Church. A Church;</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian Society</hi> called forth of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> and <hi>Jewiſh</hi> world, by God's Word and Spirit. After mention of the holy Ghoſt, the Church is mentioned in our Creed as a Work, of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Catholick,</hi> 'tis called; or Univerſal; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>New Teſtament Church</hi> conſiſts of folk of all Nations. And is not, as the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> was, confined unto one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It comprehends all the Chriſtians of all Ages, <hi>paſt, preſent,</hi> and <hi>future,</hi> in the World; which are indeed but one Body. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Holy,</hi> it's ſaid, to be, as having 1. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it's Head, Holy. 2. The <hi>bleſſed Spirit,</hi> it's Indweller, Holy. 3. The <hi>Goſpel,</hi> it's Rule, Holy. 4. All that are <hi>truly of it,</hi> are truly, tho imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Holy. 5. Their <hi>Miniſters Office,</hi> is Holy. 6. Their <hi>Worſhip,</hi> as Gods Ordinance, is Holy. 7. All <hi>Baptized members,</hi> are Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally Holy, tho' not Spiritually. <hi>Bound</hi> to the Goſpel, tho' they do not really <hi>Obey</hi> it.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>The Communion of Saints,</hi> is the <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29947:19"/> of the Holy Spirits Sanctifying of them, and the <hi>End</hi> of Church Relation. <hi>Saints</hi> are people <hi>Separated</hi> from Unclean and Common converſation, <hi>Carried</hi> by the virtue of infuſed grace unto the Fear, Love, and Service of God in Chriſt. <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> ſuppoſeth ſuch Union as is between the Members of the Body. This ſaid Communion conſiſts, 1. In their common holy <hi>Friendſhip</hi> with Father, Son and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. 2. In their <hi>mutual Love</hi> of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as themſelves. 3. In their <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>juſt Labour</hi> for each others welfare. 4. In their <hi>joyning with one Heart and Soul in God's publick Worſhip</hi> by Chriſt ordained.</p>
               <p>And The Saints of this Communion, have the <hi>Forgiveneſs of their Sins.</hi> God, for the Satisfaction and Merit of Chriſt's Obedience and Interceſſion, <hi>Pronounceth</hi> them Acquitted. And actually <hi>Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> them from the Execution of their ſin's deſerts. God may be ſaid to <hi>Puniſh them for</hi> their ſins: but not to puniſh them with <hi>the puniſhment of</hi> their Sins. 'Tis for their good, that God ever Chaſtens them.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Theſe Saints muſt alſo hereafter have <hi>the Reſurrection of their Bodies.</hi> And by conſequence have <hi>Immortal</hi> Souls. For otherwiſe, of what uſe wou'd the Bodies be? All <hi>Objections</hi> againſt this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29947:20"/> ſaid Reſurrection, be vain. Being it's ſo brightly reveal'd in <hi>Scripture.</hi> Cavillers, do not Know the <hi>Scriptures</hi> or <hi>the Power of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Life everlaſting</hi> is the portion of theſe Saints foreſaid. By Life, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>all good.</hi> And by Everlaſtingneſs, <hi>perfect Duration without Change or End.</hi> By conſequence we may determine, that Sinners dying in their ſins, ſhall have the contrary; <hi>Everlaſting Death.</hi> All Evil, without an End of any.</p>
               <p>Seems it ſtrange, that the <hi>Reward</hi> of ſhort and ſlender Obedience, ſhould be ſo Immenſe and Everlaſting? And the <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of finite Creatures ſin, in a few years committed, ſhould be of ſuch <hi>Extremity,</hi> and to all <hi>Eternity?</hi> The Wonder vaniſhes, if thou but conſider the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of the God, who ordereth the Puniſhment, and the Reward. A <hi>great</hi> God doth all things <hi>great</hi> and like Himſelf. His Rewards muſt be great, and his Puniſhments great. They would otherwiſe be a <hi>Reproach</hi> unto Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen,</hi> is here, as much as to ſay, I do verily Believe theſe things upon Divine <hi>Revelation,</hi> tho' they exceed the reach of my <hi>Senſe</hi> and my <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lords Prayer Truths</hi> eight.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:29947:20"/>
               <p n="1">1. There is a God <hi>eternal,</hi> unto whom we may and ought to <hi>Repair,</hi> for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of all our wants. Even, as a Child unto his Father. For tho' He be in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> that is, be of incomprehenſible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: and cannot without a <hi>vaſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention, regard and affect the <hi>beſt</hi> of creatures; yet He is by <hi>Creation</hi> Father. And by <hi>Redemption</hi> in Chriſt. ['Tis Sin, for the worſt of Sinners alive, to ſay, "God redeemed not me.] He is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of penitent Believers, by <hi>Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Adoption</hi> alſo. <hi>Bare wants</hi> do not deſtroy men. 'Tis <hi>neglect of right Repair</hi> unto the Lord, (that is, a <hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly</hi> Father, and <hi>our</hi> Heavenly Father,) that <hi>can</hi> and <hi>doth</hi> undo the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Exaltation of God's <hi>Name,</hi> and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto his <hi>Authority,</hi> and Obedience unto his <hi>Will and Precept,</hi> are the chief <hi>End</hi> of Man. For theſe He <hi>Made</hi> us. And for theſe He <hi>Redeem'd</hi> us. For theſe by his Word and Spirit He <hi>Calls</hi> us. For theſe we live. Yet unto all and each of theſe, are <hi>all men</hi> inſufficient. For <hi>Will. Skill,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> unto theſe, all men, (the <hi>beſt,</hi> the <hi>worſt,</hi> and <hi>middle ſort,</hi>) all are to Pray unto Him. I, and in the very <hi>firſt place</hi> to Pray.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Bread,</hi> or the neceſſaries of this Life,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29947:21"/> and <hi>Pardon of Sin,</hi> and <hi>Preventive Grace</hi> reſtraining from Sin, are the <hi>Means</hi> unto that foreſaid <hi>End.</hi> To the Exaltation, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and Obedience aforeſaid. For other Ends <hi>only,</hi> or <hi>chiefly,</hi> they may not be deſired or prayed for. 'Tis Self-Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to deſire <hi>one</hi> bit of Bread, or the Pardon of <hi>one</hi> Sin, or the repulſe of <hi>one</hi> Temptation, either <hi>ſingularly,</hi> or <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally</hi> for our own Ends. To wit, that our <hi>Bodies</hi> may not ſuffer, or our <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Bodies</hi> ſuffer, or our <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> ſuffer. But for the formentioned Ends they muſt be <hi>Deſired.</hi> And more; they muſt be <hi>Prayed for, Begged</hi> with all humble Importunity. We are infinitely unworthy of them. Our Prayers deſerve not God's beſtowing them. But our Prayer is the only way, in which God <hi>warrants</hi> our expectation of them. And in which, He gives ground to expect them without doubting. There is a kind of <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> which Holy Prayer is honoured with by <hi>Free Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Conſervation of our Beings,</hi> is the firſt of our Perſonal wants; <hi>Pardon of Sin,</hi> is the ſecond; <hi>Deliverance from Temptation, and Sin,</hi> is the third. [Reader, mark this Order. And Deſire them in this Order. Let the <hi>Shame</hi> be on me, if thou loſe by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29947:21"/> this <hi>Uſe.]</hi> If God preſerve us not in <hi>Being,</hi> we are then incapable of Doing and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any good. <hi>Being,</hi> we therefore firſt pray for. If God <hi>Pardon</hi> not our Sins, our Being is a curſed one; and worſe than none at all. For we cannot avoid his Wrath, which is the <hi>Hell</hi> of <hi>Hell. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> therefore we pray for in the ſecond place. If God deliver us not from ſinful <hi>Temptation's prevalence,</hi> our Being and paſt Pardon are very ſorry things. For Sin, after Pardon, is <hi>worſe</hi> Sin; and 'twill kindle a <hi>worſe</hi> Wrath of God. And what then becomes of us? <hi>Deliverance from it</hi> we therefore Pray for in the third place. We content us not to Pray but for the two former. We Pray for <hi>all theſe;</hi> and in this natural Method that our dear <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi> teaches.</p>
               <p n="5">5. High and honourable <hi>Thoughts</hi> of God, muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in all that Pray unto Him. And muſt be <hi>expreſſed</hi> in the entrance of their Prayer. The <hi>Preface</hi> of the Lord's Prayer ſo teacheth us. <hi>Father,</hi> ſignifies Creator, Ruler, Benefactor. Theſe words, <hi>Art in Heaven,</hi> do not ſpeak God's <hi>place;</hi> for He is every where, and is Place it ſelf. They ſignifie God's <hi>eternally being of ſuch Perfections;</hi> as neare above our minds, as the Heavens are above the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29947:22"/> Earth. <hi>Our</hi> Father, alſo ſpeaks much; <hi>Our,</hi> doth expreſs Him to be the whole <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>World</hi>'s Father I, and ſo Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Father, that He has bound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren every <hi>one,</hi> to Love and Pray for <hi>all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Kingdom, Power,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> are the three ſteps by which our Minds riſe in the Praiſe of God. <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſignifies his juſt <hi>Right</hi> to govern all things. <hi>Power,</hi> ſignifies his perfect <hi>Strength</hi> wherewith to do it. <hi>Glory,</hi> ſignifies his forth-ſhining <hi>Excellency</hi> which does and will for ever be in it. The Excellency, I mean, of all his <hi>Perfections.</hi> We do, or ſhould, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of God as a Ruler moſt rightful, and powerful, and amiable, or beautiful.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Praiſe,</hi> that is the higheſt of all Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, muſt not be <hi>ſparingly</hi> uſed in Prayer. The <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Concluſion</hi> of the Lord's Prayer, are an <hi>Heaven</hi> if all of the Stars of Praiſe! And no wonder: for <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> are comprehenſive of all God's Perfections. <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> it ſelf, which is a Worſhip more noble than that which is more on <hi>the receiving hand:</hi> it confiders but the Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Yea, and that it ſelf but little more, than as it derives and ſtreams unto us. But, <hi>Praiſe</hi> conſiders and exalts God, both
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29947:22"/> as Great and as Good. In Himſelf, and to us Good. <hi>Praiſing God,</hi> can never be enough Prais'd or Practiſed by Us, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50. <hi>penult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Prayer is as neceſſarily to be Ended with <hi>Amen,</hi> as to be Begun with <hi>Our Father.</hi> My meaning is; it muſt be concluded by all means, with <hi>Deſire, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Hope. Amen,</hi> ſignifies all. <hi>Liſtleſneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> and <hi>Want</hi> of waiting and looking for Prayers returns, do make Prayers as no Prayers. Without the Heart's actual <hi>Amen</hi> after Prayer, you interpretatively ſay, <q rend="inline">Lord, my mind's already <hi>altered.</hi> I, now am <hi>indifferent</hi> whether Thou doſt grant or deny me. I believe Thou wilt <hi>Deny.</hi> And I will not wait or look for thy <hi>Grant.</hi>
                  </q> Without an <hi>Amen</hi> with the mouth uttered, ſome do ſuppoſe the Congregation injured. 'Tis certain, where holy <hi>Amen's</hi> be not found, Prayers be loſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Commandment Truths <hi>twelve.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Object</hi> unto whom all ſupreme worſhip is to be <hi>paid,</hi> is God Only. To Him it muſt be paid, by all <hi>Souls,</hi> in all <hi>times,</hi> with all <hi>ſtrength.</hi> And unto no other. 'Tis Treaſon to pay a <hi>penny Tribute</hi> to a rebellious <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi> Or, to worſhip with divine worſhip, any tempting Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29947:23"/> If Jeſus Chriſt were not <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Eternal nature,</hi> I would not be <hi>Baptized</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his name. Or, Pray unto <hi>Him,</hi> any more than unto a <hi>Star.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis as neceſſary that God be the <hi>Author,</hi> as the <hi>Object</hi> of all religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; We muſt give Him no worſhip, but ſuch as is preſcribed by his Word. His Worſhip muſt ſuit his bleſſed <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Will.</hi> And who can Know them, but by his Word? <hi>Idolatry</hi> is officious foolery. <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> a like Phrenzy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis not enough to worſhip the true God by the true Will of God for the <hi>Matter</hi> of it; but the <hi>Manner</hi> alſo muſt be far from Prophane. It muſt be with holy <hi>Reverence</hi> and humble <hi>Complacence,</hi> and hearty <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis not enough to worſhip the true God, by the true <hi>Rule,</hi> in the true and right <hi>Manner;</hi> unleſs we alſo keep holy unto Him all ſuch <hi>Time,</hi> as He demands from us. Such portions of every <hi>Day time,</hi> and ſuch of every <hi>Weeks time.</hi> [For the Lords-day, againſt Judaizers, read Mr. <hi>Ben,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>] Holy Obſervance of the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and of <hi>hour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Worſhip</hi> on our own days, is the <hi>Practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of men ſincere.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Obedience to all the former Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29947:23"/> ſufficeth not, without <hi>Duty unto Men.</hi> Eſpecially <hi>Superiors.</hi> Principally, Honor of <hi>Parents natural.</hi> The which, are our Governors in <hi>time</hi> before Kings. On a deeper <hi>foundation</hi> than that of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, even of very Nature. To them are we moſt <hi>Obliged:</hi> and by them moſt <hi>Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> [Well is the 5th Command called the <hi>hinge</hi> of both Tables. I am ſure, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broke, all are broke. And would Children and Parents but do their Duties toward each other, it would make a ſweet change of our Engliſh familys. But hereof elſewhere.] Parents and Rulers, are God's <hi>Vicegerents</hi> over us: and <hi>next unto God,</hi> ſhould be Honored by us Loaded with honor, as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word is.</p>
               <p n="6">6. As, of our Duty toward man, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>juſt Honor</hi> is the firſt; Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his <hi>Life,</hi> is the next. Death takes away time of Repentance, and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mercies all. Look how near you come unjuſtly to Kill a man, ſo near you come to the <hi>Devil's firſt ſervice.</hi> From the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning he was a Murderer. And ſo near come you, to deprive him of all the good of <hi>this World;</hi> and, if he be not already Converted, to throw him into <hi>Hell.</hi> If you do Murder a man, you rob <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Countrey,</hi> of a Servant in this world.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29947:24"/>
               <p n="7">7. The third Kind of duty towards Man-kind, is preſervation of <hi>Chaſtity;</hi> in our ſelves, and others. To <hi>defile,</hi> is next to <hi>Kill</hi> one <hi>Obſcene</hi> thoughts, words, and deeds, be next unto <hi>Murderous</hi> ones. Laſcivious <hi>Goats,</hi> and bloody <hi>Wolves,</hi> be much like odious in God's eyes.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The fourth part of our Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man, is preſervation of his <hi>Eſtate.</hi> To Contemn, to Kill, or to Defile is worſe; but to <hi>Rob and Injure,</hi> in ever ſo little a matter, is a Sin that God will not let go unrevenged. Of how great infamy among men, is the name of a <hi>Thief?</hi> O that <hi>Thieves</hi> knew but God's thoughts of them!</p>
               <p n="9">9. The fifth ſort of duty to Man, is preſervation of them in their <hi>Cauſes,</hi> and <hi>Suits of Law.</hi> By bearing <hi>true witneſs,</hi> when called; and abhorring all <hi>falſe.</hi> All that tends to pervert <hi>publick Juſtice.</hi> Lyars, be <hi>Satan's Pictures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. The ſixth duty toward man, is ſuch <hi>Love of him</hi> as we bear unto our ſelves. Such diſtance from <hi>begrudging him</hi> any good, as we are at from begrudging it to <hi>our ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt Command, is a <hi>Summary</hi> of all Duty unto God; the ſecond, is a like <hi>Summary</hi> of all Duty unto Man.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Children of Men, ever ſince
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29947:24"/> the Fall, are averſe from all the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> God. Their <hi>Minds</hi> are unteachable, <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> unfaithful, <hi>Wills</hi> untractable. Elſe, what needed the <hi>New-Edition</hi> of the <hi>Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands?</hi> And why were they <hi>ſo</hi> delivered, as we read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.20?</p>
               <p n="12">12. The <hi>Motives</hi> that God giveth, and we ought to take and urge our hearts withal, unto the <hi>Obedience</hi> of every of God's <hi>Laws,</hi> are three.</p>
               <p>The three contained in God's <hi>Preface</hi> unto the <hi>Ten Commandments.</hi> Which are, God's <hi>Soveraignty</hi> over us, his <hi>Covenant</hi> with us, his <hi>Redemption-grace</hi> and bounty unto us. Wo unto our beſt Motions, which theſe three do not move to!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sacramental-Truths</hi> five.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Law</hi> of God for Sacraments, is not <hi>Natural,</hi> but <hi>Poſitive.</hi> He required them not, becauſe their uſe is good, antecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. No: their Uſe is therefore only good, becauſe He requires them. From whence it follows, that tho' it be impoſſible not to Uſe the Sacraments but we muſt <hi>offend</hi> God, becauſe God has commanded them: 'tis very poſſible to uſe Sacraments, and not <hi>pleaſe</hi> God. Becauſe God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them not for their own ſakes, but for certain Ends. Which Ends, if we do not <hi>aim</hi> at, and <hi>anſwer,</hi> in our uſe of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29947:25"/> the Sacraments, God has no pleaſure, and we no profit by our uſe of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>End</hi> for which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd Sacraments, is <hi>his Teſtifying</hi> his Mind and Will unto Us. And <hi>our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying back</hi> our Hearts toward Him. 'Tis true; God's Word is a Teſtimony of his Will; a <hi>firſt,</hi> a <hi>ſweet,</hi> and a <hi>ſure</hi> Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. But it has pleaſed Him to add a <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſort</hi> of Teſtification of his Covenant-Will. And by Viſible Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his own appointing, to Teſtifie it farther. As after their Word given, Men uſe by Sign and Seal to teſtifie their Minds. Likewiſe we, at our firſt Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by our <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Mouths</hi> teſtifie unto God our Wills, henceforward for ever to be his. But it pleaſeth God to require our <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>more publick, ſolemn</hi> Teſtification thereof. To wit, in and by the uſe of thoſe Rites and Ceremonies which he has preſcribed. Now, if we aim not at both theſe Ends in the uſe of Sacraments; and anſwer not theſe Ends, we mock God and delude our ſelves in their uſe. Other Ends of Sacraments there be, I know; but theſe are the chief, and comprehenſive of all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Order</hi> of the two Sacraments, of the <hi>Goſpel New-Covenant,</hi> is this, <hi>Holy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29947:25"/> Baptiſm enters</hi> a Diſciple of Chriſt; makes him that was before Covenanted, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>by Sign and Seal Covenanted</hi> with God. The <hi>Lord's Supper, renews</hi> that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant betwixt God and a Baptized Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Jeſus Chriſt. Both Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper do <hi>confirm</hi> the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; <hi>mutually,</hi> upon God's part, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ours; and <hi>extenſively,</hi> as to all the <hi>Promiſes</hi> in the Covenant from God unto us, and as to all the <hi>Demands</hi> in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, from us unto God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> of the Holy Sacraments, is ſurpaſſing. In no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances has God condeſcended ſo Low unto us, as in theſe. In none therefore, has he ſo much honoured us, as in theſe. The Apoſtle reckons Sacraments, as the prime of Church-Priviledges, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. As for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs,</hi> they are Towers of <hi>David,</hi> builded for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Armories<note n="(a)" place="margin">Of all the outward Means of Grace, the moſt Mighty.</note> We cannot warrantably expect the Holy Spirit to make the Word a-near ſo helpful to us without the Sacraments, as with them. If ordinarily He ſhould ſo do, He would diſparage them. But to be ſure, He will never do that.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Way to improve</hi> the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29947:26"/> unto Holineſs and Comfort, is by a double Pleading of them. By <hi>Pleading them with our own Souls,</hi> upon God's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. And this, either when we would bring them out of a bad frame into a good: or from a leſs holy unto a more holy frame for God. By (then) urging our hearts in ſuch like words, <q rend="inline">My Soul, my Soul, why againſt God? or why ſo coldly for Him? The Kingdom of <hi>Hell</hi> ſuffers violence. Violent Sinners take it by <hi>Force.</hi> And wilt not thou take the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven</hi> by it? Sinners be Patient Creatures; they forſake Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, take up their Croſs, and follow Satan; and thorough many tribulations enter the Kingdom of Hell. Bluſh and bleed thou, to think, that thy Patience ſhould be ſhort of theirs! and that thou ſhouldſt not without regret enter the Kingdom of Heaven that's <hi>better,</hi> thro' Tribulations that be <hi>leſſer</hi> than theirs. Think, think my Soul! Thou art <hi>Baptiz'd;</hi> the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for thy Encouragement and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has ſign'd and ſeal'd his Covenant with thee! Thou haſt been at his <hi>Holy Table;</hi> He has again and again ſign'd and ſeal'd it. Canſt thou, thou a <hi>ſign'd, ſeal'd Covenanter,</hi> Diſtruſt or
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29947:26"/> Diſobey? Thou, a <hi>frequently repeated Covenanter,</hi> and an <hi>early</hi> one too? O for ſhame, ſtir up thy ſelf, and on with the Armour of God; and follow the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of thy Salvation; and fight (not flouriſh) againſt Fleſh, World and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, according to thy Sacramental En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement! Shew that it is unto thee a Covenant of <hi>Salt,</hi> not of <hi>Snow.</hi> An <hi>Adamantine</hi> bond, not a <hi>Rope of Sand,</hi> &amp;c.</q> Again, we muſt alſo humbly <hi>Plead them with our heavenly Father,</hi> upon our own behalf. Under <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> by any evil, or <hi>Deprivation</hi> of any good, we may and ought to plead them, in Prayer before Him. 'Tis often that Miniſters do preſs Chriſtians to plead the <hi>Promiſes.</hi> I would that we (all) as often preſs'd them, to plead the ſame as <hi>ſign'd and ſeal'd.</hi> God hath not a Promiſe but what is ſign'd and ſeal'd in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and in the <hi>Holy Supper.</hi> And we plead them but imperfectly, and at halves, when we plead them not as <hi>ſign'd and ſeal'd.</hi> Go, <hi>diſtreſſed Chriſtian,</hi> fill thy mouth with the arguments of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Grace, and plead thy Cauſe at the <hi>Throne</hi> of Grace, to this purpoſe. <q rend="inline">O thou that canſt not <hi>Lye,</hi> thou haſt <hi>ſworn</hi> unto me, that in thy Goſpel-way I ſhall have Grace, Glory, and have
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29947:27"/> no good thing with-held from me. Thou ſignedſt and ſealedſt Promiſe hereof to me, in my <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> and ſo haſt thou done again and again, at <hi>thy Table.</hi> I, in thy Goſpel-way, have waited, do wait, and will to my laſt breath, thro' thy grace, wait; O Lord, canſt thou chuſe but perform what thou haſt ſo, ſo <hi>Promiſed,</hi> ſo <hi>Sworn,</hi> ſo <hi>Engag'd under Sign and Seal,</hi> &amp;c?</q> This is the way to <hi>Mortifie</hi> Corruptions, <hi>Repel</hi> Temptations, <hi>Quicken</hi> Graces, <hi>Revive</hi> Hopes, <hi>Attain</hi> Joys unſpeakable and full of Glory. O that our beſt <hi>Pulpits</hi> were leſs ſilent, and our beſt <hi>Pues</hi> leſs Ignorant, of the practick uſe of Holy Sacraments!</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:29947:27"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Q 3.</hi> What is that Change wrought in a Man by God's Holy Word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, before he can ſafely conclude himſelf to be paſſed from Death to Life?</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BY one man ſin entred into the World, and Death by ſin,</hi> Rom. 5.12. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan was a <hi>Murderer</hi> from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. He ſlew <hi>Adam</hi> by the <hi>firſt ſin:</hi> And ſlew all mankind in that <hi>firſt Adam.</hi> Spiritually conſidered, we are all <hi>Dead born.</hi> Dead <hi>in</hi> ſin, and Dead <hi>for</hi> it. Dead in reſpect of <hi>Corruption,</hi> Dead in reſpect of <hi>Condemnation.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to the <hi>Priſon</hi> of Hell, to the <hi>Torment</hi> of Fire, to the <hi>Duration</hi> of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>But <hi>God hath ſo loved the World, that he hath given his only begotten Son</hi> to redeem us from ſo great a Death, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. He deſires not our Death to be Continued, and Ruin to be Compleated. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29947:28"/> 
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the way from Death to Life. He <hi>Commands,</hi> and He even <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeches</hi> us, to take Him for our Way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <p>If you ask, by what Steps? I have told you in my <hi>Call to Sinners,</hi> by three Steps. Namely, by <hi>Conviction,</hi> by <hi>Compunction</hi> or Humiliation, and by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> unto Chriſt. Which Steps if you take aright, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to <hi>Loſe</hi> Heaven if you do not <hi>Find</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Indeed, <hi>unaſſiſtedly</hi> no man can take them. Whatever is a Creature, hath no Power but what is Given from God, and Kept by Him. But Man a faln Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, until he be by grace raiſed again, is <hi>without ſtrength</hi> unto that we ſpeak of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6. Knowledge, Will, and Power hereto are all the <hi>Gifts</hi> of God's Love, and the <hi>Purchaſes</hi> of his Son's Blood, and the <hi>Works</hi> of his Holy Spirits Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs. That Holy Spirit, who conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worketh by the Holy Word. Who wrought not Chriſt's victory over Satan, without the uſe of the Word: And will not, without it, work our Victory over him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſſible</hi> it is. And <hi>Neceſſary</hi> it is, for all that take this way to Life aforeſaid, to Enſure their ſo doing, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29947:28"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>ult.</hi> &amp;c. Uncertainty about it, is the <hi>Effect</hi> of ſin. God doth not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, if ever, with-hold Aſſurance from his Children, but upon Provocation. To wit, by Indulged <hi>Luſts,</hi> by Unexerciſed <hi>Graces,</hi> by Omitted <hi>Duties,</hi> by Slighted <hi>Ordinances.</hi> And to be ſure, Uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is then it ſelf a <hi>ſin,</hi> when 'tis merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly procured by ſin. The eyes are very blind that ſee not, how fruitful a <hi>Cauſe</hi> of ſin it is. And as hard are the hearts, that dread it not as a ſin, an Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of ſin, and a Cauſe of ſin. I grant that all Aſſurance attainable on Earth, is <hi>Imperfect.</hi> But, by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> leave, that which is attainable is both <hi>True, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> and <hi>Powerful. True</hi> and <hi>Proper,</hi> as built upon proper and eternally true Grounds for it. <hi>Powerful,</hi> as operative of Peace and Joy in our ſelves and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Thankſgiving unto God.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, 'tis very long before moſt of God's <hi>Children</hi> know their <hi>Father.</hi> And ceaſe from tormenting fear that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is he. In the firſt Converſion of the <hi>Gentile</hi> world unto Chriſt, it was not ſo. The Holy Spirit did then for the moſt part Witneſs grace, whereſoever He did work it in any. Nay, to go no farther back; Our <hi>old Engliſh Puritans,</hi> of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29947:29"/> Memory, had Aſſurance more plenty among them, than 'tis ſeen in our day. Nor wanted they our <hi>Light,</hi> ſo much as we want their <hi>Heat. Horreſco referens.</hi> Unacquaintedneſs with the Covenant of grace, breeds every where <hi>groundleſs Hopes,</hi> and as <hi>unreaſonable Fears.</hi> I ſpeak as I find: With ſome of our people, every <hi>ſhadow</hi> of Turning goes for <hi>ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> Converſion. And with others, that which is right ſubſtantial Converſion, goes for but a ſhadow of Turning. Of Turning from Death to Life.</p>
            <p>With fear and trembling I aſſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to reſolve this Queſtion. <hi>Plainly,</hi> that I may be underſtood; <hi>Briefly,</hi> that I may be remembred; <hi>Fully,</hi> that my End may be attained; in making Sinners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of their <hi>Peace,</hi> and Good men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of their <hi>Trouble.</hi> If my Method be new, my Doctrine is not. I do go forth <hi>by the foot-ſteps of Chriſt's flock;</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this Paper be made ſucceſsful by his Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>That Change after which we enquire, appears a five-fold one. Namely of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Covenant, Qualities, Converſation,</hi> and <hi>Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>C. 1. Of SPIRIT. Man, is an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied Spirit. His <hi>Body,</hi> is (we know
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29947:29"/> not how,) Indwelt and Actuated by his Spirit. His <hi>Spirit,</hi> tho' it be a Free Agent, is (in as unaccountable a way,) Indwelt and Influenced by ſome other Spirit. In our <hi>Created ſtate,</hi> the Holy Spirit was in us, and ſwayed us. Now, in our <hi>Corrupted ſtate,</hi> 'tis Satan that is in us, and leads us. 'Tis certain, that by the Firſt Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion we forfeited and loſt the foreſaid <hi>Sanctifier:</hi> And deſerved to be given up, and were given up, to the laſt named <hi>Tempter.</hi> Satan is now called the <hi>God of this World.</hi> And, <hi>He that is in the World,</hi> 1 John 4.4. <hi>The Prince—that works in the Children of Diſobedience, Epheſ.</hi> 2.3<note n="*" place="margin">Works energe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically. And like as <hi>Fire</hi> in <hi>Iron</hi> worketh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting it into a huge likeneſs unto its own Nature.</note>. And ſuch Children are named, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>not having the Spirit;</hi> to wit, the Holy One, <hi>Jude ver.</hi> 19. But in our <hi>Renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtate,</hi> there's a change of the Actuating Spirit. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is depoſed and caſt out, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. The Holy Spirit is <hi>Sent, Given, Adminiſtred, Put into</hi> us, <hi>Poured out on</hi> us, <hi>Comes on</hi> us, <hi>Reſts on</hi> us, <hi>Leads</hi> us. Is ſaid to be <hi>He, that is in</hi> Believers, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.4. Yea, and to be <hi>great in them.</hi> That is, in them to be mighty, and victorious over the aſſaulting impure Spirit.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:29947:30"/>
            <p>Looks he then like a Soul paſſed from Death to Life, in whom there's no ſuch change of the ruling Spirit? I trow not. Nor can it be ſaid, becauſe theſe Spirits forenamed be both Inviſible; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the change of them is hardly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable. Let theſe plain things be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. They are infinitely <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlike</hi> ones. Yea perfectly <hi>Contrary</hi> unto each other. They are alſo moſt <hi>Active,</hi> both of them. Satan always worketh to the utmoſt of his Power; the Holy Spirit works ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Will and Pleaſure. But both do work continually and ſtrongly. Nor are their <hi>Natures</hi> ſo Inviſible, but that their <hi>Operations</hi> are as much Senſible. Satan carries unto evil; and ſo does the H. Ghoſt carry unto good. Of all things, Satan averteth and turns away Souls from Jeſus Chriſt; from his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel.</hi> And of all things, the Holy Ghoſt carrieth Souls unto the Study and Acceptation of both. His great work is to <hi>Receive of Chriſt's,</hi> and <hi>ſhew it unto us, John</hi> 16.14. His firſt work, is to convince (as of Sin in general, ſo) principally of the Sin of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief</hi> on Chriſt. Of its being the only Sin, that does keep men in all Sin. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us alſo of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt;</hi> its <hi>Perfection</hi> in it ſelf, its <hi>Communicableneſs</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:29947:30"/> unto us, and its <hi>Acceptableneſs</hi> with God. Of its being the only, that God will accept, whatever men conceit of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> Righteouſneſs or of <hi>Legal.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince likewiſe of the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of Chriſt over all his and our Enemies. His having <hi>Subjugated</hi> Satan, as well as <hi>Satisfied</hi> God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.9, 10, 11. But I forbear. See his twelve <hi>Convictions,</hi> in my Call unto Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; together with his <hi>Humiliation-work,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion-work.</hi> Having United us unto Chriſt, no doubt but he Actuates us for Him. So the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. But that falls under conſideration elſewhere.</p>
            <p>To conclude this particular; Let the <hi>Enquiring Chriſtian</hi> thus argue! <hi>Chriſt</hi> is mine, before Life is mine! <hi>Chriſt and his Spirit</hi> are always given together. If his Holy Spirit be put into me, Satan is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. The Holy Spirit and the Unclean, cannot <hi>reign</hi> together. By the Temper of my Heart and Ways, toward Chriſt eſpecially, it's not hard to know whether he be expelled, or ſtill hold the Throne in my Soul. Theſe I will diligently watch. And examine whoſe Superſcription they bear; whether the H. <hi>Advocate's,</hi> or the <hi>Enemy's.</hi> Enemies lead to <hi>Death,</hi> Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to <hi>Life.</hi> By my <hi>Guide,</hi> I will judge
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29947:31"/> of my <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>End.</hi> And Him I will account to be my Guide, whom I do <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily</hi> and <hi>allowedly,</hi> and moſt <hi>deſirouſly</hi> follow: whether it be the Holy Ghoſt, or the contrary Spirit. If I find, that it's but now and then, when terrors force it, that I <hi>diſguſt</hi> Satan's ſuggeſtions, or <hi>reliſh</hi> the Holy Spirit's: that deliberately and freely I uſe to <hi>embrace</hi> Satan's, and reject His: that ſet aſide the next World's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, I ſhould deſire rather that Satan led me in a <hi>Senſual</hi> Life, than the Holy Ghoſt in an <hi>Evangelical:</hi> I will tell my Soul, and all that is within me, plainly, as <hi>John</hi> 5.42. <hi>I know you that ye have not the Love of God in you.</hi> On the contrary, if I find all; and diſcern that tho' I have been a Cage to the uncleaneſt Bird, yet I am by grace turn'd into a <hi>Temple</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt: that the very ſelf-ſame Spirit that dwelt in Chriſt, dwells in me: that as little as yet I know, He's daily a <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> me; as Forgetful as I am, He brings daily the things of my peace unto my <hi>Remembrance;</hi> as Dull as I am, He daily by one thought or other <hi>Quickens</hi> me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my duty, ſo that I dare not omit it; as ſad and ſour as I am, He denies me not all <hi>Comfort,</hi> but every day ſweetens ſome Word of God or other unto me; as often
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29947:31"/> as I am out of Frame for Communion with God, and that is too often, He lets me not alone till I am in again, and am <hi>Reſtored.</hi> If thus I find, I will conclude there cannot but be Life where there is ſuch a Spirit. And there cannot but be the beſt Spirit, where there be but ſuch Operations. <hi>Hereby we know that He abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in us, by the Spirit that He hath given us,</hi> 1 John 3.24.</p>
            <p>C. 2. Of COVENANT. God ever delighted to deal with Man in the way of Covenant. He bound the firſt Man He made, and all his Poſterity, in one. One unexceptionable for the <hi>Promiſes</hi> unto us, and for the <hi>Demands</hi> from us. Theſe latter were Juſt and Good; the former Rich and Honourable. But, as we have heard, Man <hi>Fell.</hi> Unleſs I ſhall rather ſay, he <hi>Leapt</hi> into Sin. For, <hi>wilfully</hi> he brake this Covenant of Works, as we call it. Yea, and by the Fall ſo brake himſelf, that he was never able ſince to do ought pleaſing unto God. I mean, before the Renewing grace of God give ability. But this grace, God never did or will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence but in a New Covenant. All He Recovereth, He takes into New-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant relation with Himſelf. Souls <hi>mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29947:32"/> of any Covenant</hi> with God, mind no Religion:<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.8.</note> none, at leaſt, that God will accept. Thoſe <hi>that hang upon the Old Covenant</hi> of Works; and have all their Religion run in that Channel: Doing all they do, with deſign and hope to be forgiven for the ſake and merit of it: the Goſpel declares their miſtake to be mortal. <hi>They that are of the Works of the Law, are under the Curſe.</hi> That is, they that expect Life and Salvation for their own Works of the Law, are every creature of them under God's Curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. They, who being ſenſible what 'tis to be out of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and what to be under the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, do <hi>enter the New Goſpel-Covenant;</hi> the Marriage-Covenant unto Chriſt: they are the Souls, the only ones that bring forth fruit unto God. And have Life of either Peace with Him, or Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto Him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4.</p>
            <p>Surely, God never ſigned their <hi>Paſs</hi> for Heaven, who never made his Covenants the matter of many of their Thoughts. A ſerious heart cannot but ask, In what relation, more than that of a <hi>Creature,</hi> do I ſtand in unto God? As a Creature, I can deſerve no <hi>reward,</hi> whatever I do! And why ſhould I expect any? If I may
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29947:32"/> be a <hi>Covenanter,</hi> and was ſo, without my knowledge in my firſt Parents: does it not now concern me to get inform'd, what the Terms of that Covenant were? For Covenants bind <hi>mutually;</hi> and if I know not that which I am bound in, I muſt unavoidably be falſe unto it. If it be ſuch as is <hi>Good</hi> for me, I cannot improve it: and if unto me it become by any means <hi>deſtructive,</hi> I am not capable of preventing it. If the Soveraign Lord make, and offer to take me into a <hi>better Covenant;</hi> how concerned am I, above all things in this World, to learn out the terms thereof? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, ſuppoſe the <hi>greateſt ſtudy</hi> of theſe Covenants, and the <hi>beſt Acquaintance</hi> with them: the beſt that is poſſible to be without profound <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> for the Covenant of Grace, and hearty <hi>Conſent</hi> thereunto; what avails it? Much every way indeed, to mens Condemnation! Knowledge of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant without Conſent, is the moſt frightful ſymptom that I know of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">A Soul in earneſt careful to know its ſtate, ſhould in this wiſe debate with it ſelf, Were I under no Covenant, it would be reaſonable to expect Hell for my <hi>leaſt ſin.</hi> For it deſerves it: and the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29947:33"/> Divine Juſtice is unqueſtionable.</q> It would be unreaſonable, if I could yield <hi>Sinleſs Obedience,</hi> to be preſumptuous of other reward than is in the yielding of it. For in that, is more than a Creature me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. And I can make no <hi>Plea,</hi> if God make no free <hi>Promiſe.</hi> There are but two Covenants; of Works, and of Grace. Theſe are vaſtly different. And ſo are the ſtates of men, under the one and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other. Of my ſtate I am peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily reſolv'd to make Judgment, as I am under this or that. My <hi>Hopes</hi> ſhall die if I appear under that of Works; my <hi>Fears</hi> ſhall die, if I appear under this of Grace.</p>
            <p>For if I am under the Covenant of Works, I am bound unto <hi>Duties,</hi> whoſe Performance is by me <hi>Impoſſible.</hi> It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Obedience perfect and perpetual. I, and that upon pain of Death, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10, 11. Conſequently, if I am under this Covenant, I am under its <hi>Curſe</hi> too; which is <hi>Intolerable, Gen.</hi> 2.17. Dying thou ſhalt Die. 'Tis Death <hi>indefinite,</hi> that is, Univerſal evil; Temporal, Spiritual, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: Privative, Negative, Poſitive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beſides, if I am under this <hi>Works-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> I can have no Days-man or Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor between God and me. I muſt to <hi>Priſon</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29947:33"/> if I pay not, my ſelf, the utmoſt <hi>Farthing.</hi> This Covenant admits not Chriſt, or any other Advocate, with the offended Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 'Tis another Covenant that Chriſt is Mediator of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. If I am under this Covenant, the <hi>leaſt ſin,</hi> tho' I ſhed a Sea of bloody tears for it, is as unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable as the very ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Yea, and my <hi>Service,</hi> ſhould I keep all the whole Law, ſave in one point, would be utterly contemned.</p>
            <p>And all this juſtly too. Becauſe, if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Covenant I abide, 'tis of my <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> my <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> unto God and Chriſt, that I do abide ſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. I am <hi>Taught</hi> better: in the Goſpel the Righteouſneſs of God is Revealed. I am <hi>offered</hi> better: the Goſpel invites me from under the Law to Grace. From the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant that works wrath, to that which is <hi>all Salvation.</hi> And my being under the <hi>deadly Covenant,</hi> is by my own <hi>very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, Gal.</hi> 4.21.</p>
            <p>The Fruits muſt ſhew it, if I am under it. And they are plainly theſe: <hi>Bondage and Fear</hi> in ones ſpirit; a Fear keeping out the Love of God, and the very deſire to Love Him. <hi>Outſideneſs in Religious Duties.</hi> Care, abundance, about the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29947:34"/> of the Platter: none, or next to none, about the purity of the inner man, and the Intentions of the heart. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency on Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in things pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto God. For both Aſſiſtance by his Spirit, and Acceptance thro' his Blood, a fatal Undependency. <hi>Servility, ſouring and embittering all Duty.</hi> Rendring Religion a task and burthen; and all God's homage as arrant Brick and Bondage. Do theſe grapes of <hi>Sodom</hi> cover my Tree? The Axe of vengeance is then near my root.</p>
            <p>If on the other hand, I am not under the Law, but Grace. If with me, God hath made the better Covenant: what then? <hi>the bleſſing of Abraham</hi> is come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. Reconciliation, Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Adoption, are my own. I am intereſted in all the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of this beſt Covenant, as well as bound unto all the <hi>Duties.</hi> God is then my Reconciled God; and Engaged by Promiſe, to exert for my good all his Perfections. <hi>I will be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a God, Heb.</hi> 8.10. Joyntly, <hi>All;</hi> and diſtinctly, <hi>Every</hi> of the three Divine Perſons, have thus Engaged. So proves the form of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> into the name of All and Each of them: as alſo the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> which God's New-Covenant Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants do hold, with All and Each Perſon.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29947:34"/> 
               <hi>Pardoning</hi> Grace and <hi>Purifying,</hi> are expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made over to me, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8, 10. So is the <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. So is <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Rayment,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. So are <hi>Bleſſings for my Children, Gen.</hi> 17.7. I, and I have this <hi>hyperbolically</hi> kind and ſweeteſt Word of God to live on, <hi>ſc. Luke</hi> 15.31. ALL THAT I HAVE IS THINE. A word, which if I once prove my inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in, <hi>let them be poor and ſad that can, I cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtill I remember, they are Fruits that make known Roots. And the fruits of Souls that have ſo much for the better changed Covenants, are theſe. <hi>They Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their ſlavery.</hi> It runs in their minds, how the Covenant of Works (ſince the Fall) made them Vaſſals. How they were <hi>Adam</hi>'s Children, as ſoon as their Souls &amp; Bodies were united in the womb. And no ſooner <hi>Adam's</hi> Children, but under <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant. Nor ſooner under his Covenant, but under his Curſe too. <hi>They conſider much their Tranſlation out of it.</hi> Their Eye and their Heart, is upon the <hi>Father,</hi> that ſaid to Son and Spirit, <hi>Come, let us redeem Man!</hi> Upon the <hi>Son,</hi> that ſaid, <hi>Lo, I come to do thy Will!</hi> Upon the Glorious <hi>Spirit,</hi> that ſaid unto their moſt unwilling Souls once, <hi>Kiſs this Son!</hi> Bid them, yea
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29947:35"/> and Made them willing. Upon the <hi>ſweet Change</hi> alſo, that followed that willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and actual Marriage-Union to Chriſt. God no more looking on a poor Soul as the <hi>firſt,</hi> but as the <hi>ſecond Adam</hi>'s Child. No more Condemning, however Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. No more Abhorring his Services, notwithſtanding millions of unallowed and lamented Imperfections, <hi>&amp;c. They joy in the Lord, and rejoyce in the God of their Salvation.</hi> Or, <hi>Labour ſo to do, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they cannot.</hi> If no other, they ſing bleſſed <hi>Gataker</hi>'s Song.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Thirſt for Thirſtineſs. I weep for Tears;</l>
                  <l>Well-pleas'd I am to be Diſpleaſed thus:</l>
                  <l>The only thing I Fear is want of Fears;</l>
                  <l>Suſpecting I am not ſuſpitious.</l>
                  <l>I cannot chuſe but Live, becauſe I Die;</l>
                  <l>And when I am not Dead, how glad am I?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet when I am thus glad, for ſenſe of Pain,</l>
                  <l>And careful am leſt Careleſs I ſhould be;</l>
                  <l>Then do I grieve for being glad again,</l>
                  <l>And fear leſt Careleſneſs take Care from me.</l>
                  <l>Amidſt theſe reſtleſs thoughts this reſt I find,</l>
                  <l>For thoſe that Reſt not here, ther's Reſt behind.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Their higheſt ambition is to Rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus. To Glory in Him. <hi>They
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29947:35"/> Love God's Law, and Truſt his Son.</hi> They <hi>Love</hi> his Law, and have reſpect to every Command, and ſtrive after Perfection, and abound in all Duty. But, they <hi>Truſt</hi> not in any works of their own. <hi>Doing</hi> all, they cry for Chriſt's Spirit, for Strength. <hi>Having done all,</hi> they cry for Chriſt's Blood, for making it Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. They ſtill know themſelves Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants unprofitable. Is it thus with thee, O my Soul? then <hi>Return to thy reſt, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee!</hi> If thou wear any Phylactery, let this be the Scripture, <hi>All the paths of the Lord are Mercy and Truth to ſuch as keep his COVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANT, Pſal.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>C. 3. Of QUALITIES. Look as where the <hi>Spirit</hi> is Changed, the <hi>Covenant</hi> muſt needs be Changed; ſo where the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> is Chang'd, the <hi>Qualities</hi> of a Man muſt alſo be Changed. Theſe are myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things. And by many names men go about to explain them. But they are moſt, if not only, made known by their <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</hi> Conceive we of them as the <hi>Springs, Seeds,</hi> and <hi>Roots</hi> of our Thoughts, Words and Works. And the things by which we are therefore denominated, Holy or Sinful. They be the <hi>Treaſure</hi> that's in a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29947:36"/> Soul. A Treaſure for <hi>abundance,</hi> and for <hi>belovedneſs.</hi> Every man hath abundance of Moral Qualities; and all are dear unto him, precious in his Eyes. And as this Treaſure is good or evil, our Saviour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominates the man good of evil, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.35. In our <hi>firſt Creation,</hi> the concrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Qualities were ſurely good, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſo God endued all our Natural Powers, with all good and towardly Qualifications. Qualities and Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for prompt and conſtant Duty, were inlaid in our <hi>Mind, Will,</hi> yea and <hi>Senſitive part.</hi> Our ſeveral Powers and Faculties do depend much on each other for action. The Practick upon the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective Powers, and they on the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual ones, or our Underſtanding Powers. But all were made <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright,</hi> that is, with ſprings of goodneſs in them, apt to move as they ought towards each other within, and toward Objects with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. But the <hi>firſt Sin</hi> brake thoſe Springs, <hi>expelled</hi> thoſe good Qualities, <hi>introduced</hi> contrary ones. In a Subject ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of two contraries (as of Light and Darkneſs,) there will be one. Man is capable of holy Qualities and ſinful. The Sin that drave out the firſt therefore, could not but bring in the latter. And ſet ſprings
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29947:36"/> of evil in us, apt to make motions evil of all kinds. The Holy Scripture teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it did ſo; and that, not obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the very Text forecited. Plainly in others, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. Faln Man is by ſome compared to a <hi>diſorder'd Clock,</hi> that ſtrikes falſe every minute, and has not one true motion before the Maker mend it. Now, can a Holy God delight in a Creature thus Qualified? One diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to no real good, but to all evil, and that continually? If God ever <hi>Recall</hi> ſuch unto Himſelf, He will new Create them. Make them quite <hi>other Creatures. Inſtruments,</hi> moved with New Springs. <hi>Trees</hi> of other Roots. The Old Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties muſt away, and all be New. The Evil Treaſure muſt be took out, tho' it be bound up in the heart; a Good muſt be Laid in, and be a-like ſeated. Holy Qualities muſt be Infuſed.</p>
            <p>Accordingly we find every where in the Scripture, God denouncing Wrath againſt all men of unrenewed Natures. Not Renewed, that is, and Regenerated in the Qualities of the ſame; for the Nature it ſelf abideth ſtill the ſame in Converted as in Unconverted men, <hi>John</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>And on the other hand, God's Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29947:37"/> Servants are named ſuch as have Put off the <hi>Old Man.</hi> Crucified the <hi>Fleſh</hi> with its <hi>Affections</hi> and <hi>Luſts.</hi> Mortified their <hi>Members</hi> which are upon Earth; with much like. All which phraſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their Parting with their inward <hi>Roots</hi> of Sin; their <hi>Diſpoſitions</hi> and their <hi>Inclinations</hi> unto evil.</p>
            <p>They are likewiſe ſaid, to Put on the <hi>New Man.</hi> To be <hi>born again</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven. To be men of <hi>another Heart,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>New Creatures, &amp;c.</hi> That is to be now of Diſpoſitions quite contrary unto what they were before. Inclined now to things that Pleaſe God, as before unto things Offending Him. Now to Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as before unto Folly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feeling excuſeth Words.</hi> It need not be ſaid, how hard the parting from Old Qualities is. Things <hi>glued together,</hi> uſe not to come aſunder without <hi>tearing.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til an Heart be Rent, there is no coming apart from its Luſt. But the Neceſſity of the ſeparation is open to every Eye. For <hi>Gratia non perdit Naturam.</hi> God's hatred of ſin, is his very <hi>Nature:</hi> and even <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Grace</hi> cannot deſtroy his Eternal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. It implies the greateſt of contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that He who is Holineſs it fell ſhould Ceaſe to hate men of ſettled aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29947:37"/> from it; And bent unto Ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And it were <hi>blackeſt Blaſphemy</hi> for any to conceit, that Chriſt came to ſave us <hi>in</hi> our ſinful Qualities, and not <hi>from</hi> them.</p>
            <p>A Wiſe man would therefore know his <hi>Qualities,</hi> before he made his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his <hi>Condition</hi> toward God. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining, that as the Qualities are, that be predominant and reign in him; ſo is the Judgment of God on him. That this latter is <hi>Abſolving</hi> or <hi>Condemning,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the former be Holy or the contrary. It is true, contrary Qualities may poſſeſs together the ſame Heart. In <hi>low degrees</hi> they may and do. In <hi>high degrees</hi> they cannot. Grace and Luſt, are both of 'em in every the beſt Soul. But they can no more Reign together, than Water can <hi>Boil</hi> and <hi>Freeze</hi> together<note n="*" place="margin">A Luſt Reigns, when 'tis <hi>Yielded</hi> unto. <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi> be <hi>Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> as long as they are ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <hi>Reſiſted.</hi> Grace doth <hi>Reign</hi> in the Soul, while 'tis in like manner <hi>Warred</hi> and <hi>Fought</hi> for by the Soul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as Regenerated, I doubt not.</note>. So that my Enquiry muſt be, What are thoſe Qualities that have the Throne in me? That ſway my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29947:38"/> my Affections, and my Practick Powers. The Sinful Qualities that bend all theſe unto evil, are the <hi>Corruption of Nature,</hi> and <hi>Original Sin.</hi> The Holy Ones that bend all theſe unto good, are <hi>Grace,</hi> and the very <hi>New Nature</hi> in us. Whether of them do prevail in me, is my great Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Commonly, and I think juſtly, we count four Properties of a Quality or Diſpoſition's Prevalency. Namely, its cauſing to act <hi>Readily,</hi> and without much ado. <hi>Pleaſantly,</hi> and without diſguſt. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally,</hi> without excluſion of any proper Object. And <hi>Conſtantly,</hi> without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions. Now if Original Sin, carry me thus unto Actual Sin, I am <hi>far from the Kingdom of God!</hi> If Grace thus carry me unto gracious actions, <hi>the Kingdom of God is within me.</hi> To be a little more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, Holy Qualities, the Principal are <hi>three;</hi> the Inſtrumental are <hi>eight.</hi> The former are Evangelical, <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> The latter be, <hi>Prudence, Juſtice, Temperance, Courage, Sincerity, Humility, Zeal,</hi> and <hi>Conſtancy.</hi> Methinks, whether theſe, or the contraries of theſe, do (as aforeſaid) act me, ſhould be of eaſie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. Inward <hi>Feelings,</hi> and outward <hi>Fruits,</hi> one would think, ſhould not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29947:38"/> it into any doubt at all. But I am aware, <hi>Mixtures</hi> do obſcure things. And in whom are not Mixtures found? Again, Moles muſt not be expected to be as Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible as Mountains. 'Tis <hi>Greatneſs</hi> that makes conſpicuous. And where Grace's Victory is little, which is next to none, I muſt not wonder if it be as little diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Nor dare I deſire God to change the Nature of things, for me. Rather muſt I Labour to <hi>grow</hi> in Grace. And, that it may be more <hi>Viſible,</hi> blow up my ſpark to a flame. Heaven and Hell are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſibly different ſtates. And I muſt believe that God will have them to be very differently Qualified Creatures whom He placeth in the one and other. My Intereſt carries me i'th' firſt place, to ſee I have the <hi>Principle,</hi> and nextly that I have <hi>Proficience</hi> in Grace. Without the <hi>Principle</hi> I have no Qualification for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And without the <hi>Proficience,</hi> I ſhall ever doubt the truth of my Principle. A ſtrict Eye unto both will I have, before I conclude the name to Live to be my due.</p>
            <p>C. 4. Of CONVERSATION. A good <hi>Spirit</hi> brings into a good <hi>Covenant.</hi> And, according thereto, infuſeth <hi>good Qualities.</hi> But doth He then leave them idle
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29947:39"/> and dormant? No, He doth not. <hi>All Being is for Action.</hi> And the beſt Nature for the beſt Action. Beſides, Man is a creature that cannot be out of Action. Grace only carries him to act <hi>well;</hi> Corruption, to act <hi>ill;</hi> but his very Nature 'tis to act <hi>much. Man Created</hi> did exerciſe his Powers, and exert his holy Qualities, moſt amiably no doubt. Formed his <hi>behaviour,</hi> towards God, the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit;</hi> towards <hi>himſelf,</hi> and the <hi>Angels above</hi> him, and <hi>ſublunary Creatures below</hi> him, moſt congruouſly, and harmoniouſly: <hi>Faln Man</hi>'s Converſation toward all, is in the World <hi>ſeen,</hi> what in the Bible 'tis <hi>read.</hi> What is ſaid of his Thoughts, which are his inward Converſes, may be ſaid of his outward ones alſo. They are <hi>evil, only</hi> evil, and <hi>continually.</hi> Toward God, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs;</hi> toward Holy Angels and Spirits above, as <hi>Mindleſs;</hi> towards himſelf, <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous;</hi> towards his Superiours, <hi>Envious;</hi> towards Inferiors, <hi>Contemptuous;</hi> towards Equals, <hi>Jealous. Renewed Man,</hi> we read and we ſee it, hath another Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all foreſaid. A Walk, <hi>after the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> That is, according to the <hi>will and motion</hi> of the Holy Spirit the worker of Grace; and according to the <hi>gracious Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Nature</hi> of his in-working. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:29947:39"/> is a neceſſity of <hi>Precept;</hi> their God commands it, on peril of never ſeeing his Face. A neceſſity of <hi>Means; viz.</hi> for God's Glory, which they cannot ſpread without it: for the Church's good, which they cannot edifie without it: for their own Walk to Heaven, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make without it: For, tho' it be not the way of Merit, 'tis the way of Means. A neceſſity of <hi>Deſign</hi> there is alſo; for, 'tis God's End in Electing, Redeeming, and Calling them. A neceſſity of <hi>Nature:</hi> for, as naturally and neceſſarily do clean Fountains ſend forth clean Waters, as corrupt ones the contrary. Add, a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Covenant</hi> likewiſe: for, as by Gratitude, ſo by Covenant all are bound to have their Converſation as becomes the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>If theſe things be ſo, the reſolution of the three former Queſtions, excuſe me not a third. Wo to the vain men, who would cry up <hi>God's Mercy,</hi> to the Reproach of <hi>Chriſt's Merits.</hi> Or Chriſt's Merits to the undervaluing of <hi>Holy Faith.</hi> Or Faith, to the juſtling out of <hi>Good Works,</hi> and the making <hi>holy Converſation</hi> needleſs. We muſt give unto each its <hi>proper place,</hi> or Heaven will never be <hi>our place.</hi> He that thinks fit to judge by God's Word; and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:29947:40"/> to believe that God will not Deny <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> or alter his <hi>Decrees,</hi> and repeal his <hi>Laws,</hi> and change his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to ſerve the turn of a ſluggard; he muſt conclude ſo. And judge an Holy Life to be as far from <hi>Needleſs,</hi> as it is from being <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a man muſt tell himſelf to this purpoſe: <q rend="inline">Hope of Reconciliation to to God, <hi>is</hi> needful to my <hi>Peace</hi> in this Life. And will <hi>appear</hi> ſo, at Death. But <hi>Holy Converſation,</hi> is as neceſſary unto that Hope. God promiſeth not to give it, to ſuch as lead any other. Nor know I how He ſhould ſhew grounds for any to cry peace, while their Life againſt Him, is an <hi>open</hi> or a <hi>private</hi> War againſt Him.</q> Eternal thanks be to Him! I know his New Covenant will paſs that Converſation for an Holy one, which is far ſhort of <hi>Legal</hi> Perfection. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nallowed</hi> ſins, and of <hi>meer infirmity,</hi> break not peace. <hi>Wilful</hi> ones, and the moſt <hi>crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> do not raiſe a ſtorm that Chriſt's Grace cannot Lay for true Penitents. And ſuch as by their <hi>good wills</hi> would never of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend more. Ready to give the World if they had it, that they never more might ſin. Wherefore neither will I think my Converſation <hi>unholy,</hi> for that which God
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:29947:40"/> does not ſo name it. Nor will I ever expect he ſhould ſay to me, <hi>[Well done, good and faithful Servant,]</hi> if indeed by the Goſpel-ſtandard I have not done well. I verily believe God will ſay to me hereafter <hi>[Depart, thou Curſed]</hi> unleſs I Live ſo, that He may ſay to this effect of me before the World; <q rend="inline">Behold ye <hi>damned Angels,</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> whom I have for ever abandoned! No cauſe have you to think my ways <hi>unequal</hi> in ſetting this poor creature at my right hand. True, his <hi>Sins</hi> were not few or ſmall. Nor were his <hi>Obediences</hi> other than ſmall and few. Had they been perfect, they could not have ſatisfied me, for <hi>one</hi> ſin. Much leſs as they were ſhort thereof. <hi>Satisfaction</hi> and <hi>Merit</hi> I had, from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand. His holy Qualities and Works made me <hi>none.</hi> Yet do I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider his <hi>Converſation</hi> and <hi>good works</hi> as enough to diſtinguiſh him from you. And to ſtop your mouths, By them you ſee, he is one that Obeyed <hi>my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts;</hi> Uſed <hi>my appointed Means</hi> of Life; Anſwered <hi>my End</hi> in's Creation; Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the <hi>New Nature</hi> I gave him; Kept ſincerely and perſeveringly the <hi>Covenant</hi> I ſign'd and ſeal'd with him in my Holy Sacraments.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:29947:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To him that ordereth aright his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation will I ſhew the ſalvation of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 50 ult. <hi>If we ſay that we have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or friendſhip with Him, and WALK in darkneſs, we Lye, and do not the Truth: (i. e.</hi> We Lye practically, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict our Profeſſions) 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.6. <hi>God will render to every man according to his works; To them who by patient continuance in well doing, ſeek for glory and honour, and immortality, Eternal Life. But to them that are contentious, and do not obey the Truth, but obey unrighteouſneſs, indignation and wrath,</hi> Rom. 2.6, 7, 8. James 3.13. <hi>Who is a wiſe man, and endued with knowledge among you? let him ſhew out of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation his works with meekneſs of wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>C. 5. Of COMPANY. God hath made us of a Nature <hi>craving Company,</hi> as we crave <hi>Being</hi> it ſelf. Being <hi>alone,</hi> is as not Being at all. Our Souls muſt be with ſome <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Thing</hi> continually. And for <hi>Things,</hi> no man affects any but for the ſake of <hi>Perſons. Sinleſs Nature</hi> was not thought fit to be <hi>Alone. Corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is amort without corrupt Company. And ſo is <hi>Sanctified Nature</hi> without like Company. Being ſo very <hi>dear unto</hi> us,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:29947:41"/>
'tis no wonder that our Company is ſo <hi>influential on</hi> us. Yea, ſo <hi>formative of</hi> us into its likeneſs, as we ſee. Good and Evil Company, are (both of 'em) ſo, beyond what is duly conſidered. Worſt men are ſomewhat <hi>bettered</hi> by good; Beſt men are ſomewhat <hi>worſted</hi> by evil. True, while we are in the World, there is a company good and ill that <hi>of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> we ſome way have. But there is alſo a Company <hi>of choice</hi> that we make. And of this I chiefly ſpeak. The Efficacy of this, is moſt wondrous.</p>
            <p>So much, that the Holy Spirit makes a <hi>Companion of fools,</hi> the name of a <hi>hopeleſs Enemy</hi> of God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.20. And intimates it to be enough to call the beſt Saint's ſincerity in queſtion, if he <hi>walk in company</hi> (needleſly) with wicked men, <hi>Job</hi> 34.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſaving in order to do them good, forbids us to let them be in our houſes, or to ſuffer our ſelves to be with them any where, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.4, 7. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14, 15. Neither indeed is <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ought that I know, but a caſting out of our Encouraging Society, ſuch as walk diſorderly.</p>
            <p>Every where in the Word, we are told, that Love of the Godly is the mark
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:29947:42"/> of the Lovers of God. And they that fear God's Name, be ſuch as are glad to have for their company God's Children. I, and hate with a <hi>perfect hatred</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious company of others. They flock together, and to one another ſpeak of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <p>And who would not deſire to <hi>try</hi> and <hi>know</hi> himſelf, by that mark whereby other men do know him? And whereby, thro' a plain light of the Word, he may know himſelf? Yea, by the mark, without whoſe concurrence, <hi>fifties and hundreds</hi> of other marks will not be more than <hi>Cyphers.</hi> For, if my <hi>Company of choice</hi> be not changed, my <hi>Converſation</hi> is juſtly preſumed to be but ſorrily changed. And not from a Walk with men to a Walk with God; but from one way of ſin to another. My <hi>Qualities</hi> alſo and <hi>inner Temper,</hi> be juſtly thought to be but <hi>Covered,</hi> not <hi>Changed.</hi> My <hi>Change of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> may be concluded to be but in <hi>fancy,</hi> and a vain ſurmiſe. And ſo my Change of <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come therefore, my Soul, and let us reaſon together, ſaith he that is taught of God to <hi>enſure</hi> his Calling and Election. For ought I ſee by the Word of God, <hi>Dying men do change but their Places, not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:29947:42"/> their Company.</hi> And what Company I do of <hi>choice</hi> hold upon Earth, I muſt <hi>by the Judgment of God</hi> hold for ever. Prophane men be <hi>open</hi> Sepulchres; Hypocrites be <hi>painted</hi> ones. If I here delight in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, and chuſe to keep among the dead; 'tis certain I ſhall for ever with them be <hi>Buried.</hi> Chriſt is a <hi>Tree of Lives.</hi> Of the Life of <hi>Peace</hi> with God, <hi>Holineſs</hi> toward Him, <hi>Hope</hi> from Him, <hi>Glory</hi> with Him. Saints only have Life from Chriſt, and be the only men that are truly Alive. If the <hi>Spirit</hi> that acts me, and <hi>Covenant</hi> that binds me, and <hi>Qualities</hi> that poſſeſs me, and <hi>Converſation</hi> that employs me, do all of 'em bring me among the Living; and I am their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion in <hi>Graces-Kingdom,</hi> ſurely I ſhall be the ſame in <hi>Glories-Kingdom</hi> too.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, before I ſhall conclude <hi>whither 'tis I am going,</hi> I will get me well aſſured what the Company is <hi>wherewith I go.</hi> I will be fully anſwer'd theſe Queſtions: Am I in evil Company, as <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> Vexed? Is Lewd Company and Light, unto me, which <hi>Meſech</hi> and <hi>Kedar</hi> was to <hi>David?</hi> Makes it me to cry, <hi>Wo is me?</hi> Have I no fellowſhip with God's Enemies, but Reprove I them as called? Do I make the very wide
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:29947:43"/> difference that I ought, between MEN and BRETHREN? Do I fear to open the doors of my Houſe and Heart to ill men, leſt the <hi>Prince of darkneſs</hi> enter in? And to ſhut them againſt holy Brethren, leſt the <hi>Prince of Glory</hi> be ſhut out? Am I glad when I ſee the <hi>Pure in heart,</hi> that ſee God? Do I ſalute each of them as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Abigail? Bleſſed be the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>which ſent thee this day to meet me? Bleſſed be thy converſe, and bleſſed be thou.</hi> I ſay, Every of them, <hi>viz.</hi> Tho' about <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Cummin</hi> differently mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And tho' by their <hi>Luſtre,</hi> I am <hi>eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp;c.</hi> Finally, Do I <hi>Love</hi> them that Love God, and <hi>Loath</hi> them that Loath Him, even as I incline to have my friends Love thoſe that Love me, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? And do theſe following words of God dwell in me richly and powerfully, <hi>Lord who ſhall abide in thy Tabernacle? Who ſhall dwell in thy Holy Hill? He, in whoſe Eyes a Vile perſon is contemned, but he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth them that fear the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 15.1, 4. <hi>They that fear thee (O Lord) will be glad when they ſee me (that is, a Godly man,)</hi> Pſal. 119.74. <hi>He that walks with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe, but a Companion of fools ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> or broken, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.20.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:29947:43"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Deſires</hi> of ſome, and ſuppoſed <hi>Needs</hi> of others, invite me to place here this ſhorter Solution of the third Queſtion.</p>
            <p>The Change in us, which ſheweth Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to be come on us, is twofold; <hi>Intellectual,</hi> and <hi>Practical.</hi> Of our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and of our Converſations [We do not Omit that of the <hi>Affections,</hi> but comprehend it in the other.]</p>
            <p>The <hi>Intellectual Change</hi> is then, and not till then, when four things are Learned, and are alſo a Learning better by us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt.</hi> The Doctrines which are the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. We have ſhewn them, upon the ſecond Queſtion. Who can think him ſavingly Built on Chriſt, that knows not the very firſt Stones to be laid in that Spiritual Building?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Concluſions from the Principles foreſaid.</hi> The Doctrines, that are for Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:29947:44"/> on Chriſt. Theſe alſo have been ſet forth with the fore-mentioned. Building on, is as neceſſary as the Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Foundation is. Neither is it ſavingly Laid, where the Holy Spirit is not teaching, and a Soul learning to Build up and Build on. To wit, that it may become a complete Temple for the Holy Spirit, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12, 13, 15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Confirmations of the ſaid Principles.</hi> The Doctrines Proving, and Strengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. And Warranting our Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Superſtructure; Securing 'em againſt Winds of Oppoſition. 'Tis as needful to cover and preſerve what we build, from the injuries of weather, as it is to build, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12, 16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Applications of the mention'd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi> The Doctrines directing their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement unto Duties, as well Relative, as Perſonal. What are Means worth, but for the Ends of them? What good do all Truths in our Minds, if not improved unto all holy Services in our Lives? Who would Build and Cover a Houſe, but for Uſe to themſelves and their Friends? Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly, the Spirit has not Built and Strengthned us in Chriſt, if he has not
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29947:44"/> taught us to make our Life a ſervice to Him. And to make His Will, not our own, our Law and Rule. Our Rule, for behaviour toward God, Our Selves, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Friends, Enemies, Superiors, Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, Equals.</p>
            <p>The ignorant, and the liſtleſs to know the firſt of theſe be <hi>Owls</hi> and <hi>Bats.</hi> Thoſe that be the like, to know the ſecond, be <hi>Dwarfs,</hi> yea <hi>Embryo's.</hi> Souls regardleſs to know the third, be <hi>Sand-builders,</hi> and lie at the mercy of the Weather. And the mindleſs of the fourth, be <hi>barren Heaths.</hi> All <hi>ſhort</hi> of what they ſhould be: yea <hi>contrary</hi> to what they muſt be, if ever they paſs from Death to Life.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Practical Change</hi> is then, when four things can be ſaid of a Man.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That he is Changed as far as</hi> Felix, Agrippa, <hi>and</hi> Herod. That he is one that Trembles at God's Word. Has an Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be a very Chriſtian. Hears the Word preach'd gladly. Otherwiſe he is not ſo much as a Waſhed, Swine, or Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sepulchre.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That he is Changed farther; and as a Stone into a Flame of Fire.</hi> A Stone, is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29947:45"/> Dark, Cold, and Inclines downward to its earthy Centre. Fire is Bright, Hot Active, and that Upward. To ſay a Man is thus Changed, is to ſay that of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, he is made Knowing. Of <hi>Liſtleſs,</hi> he is made Zealous for God in Chriſt. Of <hi>Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious for Earth,</hi> he is made ſo for Heaven</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That he is Changed into the Man of God by Saint</hi> Paul<hi>'s Character.</hi> That is, a man throughly furniſhed for every good work. I mean every one, from him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired as a Church-Member, <hi>e. gr.</hi> For <hi>Reading</hi> and <hi>Hearing</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> profitably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for Uſing of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> ſo; and for ſubmitting unto <hi>Church-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> ſo; Not to ſay, for <hi>Governing his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> holily, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are imported. By being furniſhed hereto, I underſtand pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with neceſſary <hi>Skill</hi> and <hi>Zeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That he is Changed from a</hi> Demas <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Martyr.</hi> That is, that of a fearer of the Croſs more than of the Loſs of the immortal Crown, he be made in reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a <hi>Martyr.</hi> And become reſolved, by God's grace, to die any the <hi>worſt</hi> death rather than commit any the <hi>leaſt</hi> ſin. To be ſalted with fiery Tryals, rather than with Hell's fire.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:29947:45"/>
            <head>Books Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel.</head>
            <p n="1">1. OF Thoughtfulneſs for the Morrow, with an Appendix concerning the Immoderate Deſire of Fore-knowing things to come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Redeemer's Tears wept over loſt Souls, in a Treatiſe on <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. With an Appendix wherein ſomewhat is occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally diſcourſed concerning the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and how God is ſaid to Will the Salvation of them that periſh.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of Charity in Reference to other Mens Sins.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Sermon directing what we are to do after a ſtrict inquiry whether or no we truly love God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Two Sermons Preached at <hi>Thurlow</hi> in <hi>Suffolk;</hi> on thoſe words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13.—<hi>Yield your ſelves to God.</hi> All Five by <hi>J. How.</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Heaven or Hell upon Earth: Or, a Diſcourſe concerning Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The True Touch-Stone which ſhews both Grace and Nature.
<pb facs="tcp:29947:46"/> Or, a Diſcourſe concerning Self-Examination, by which both Saints and Sinners may come to know themſelves. Whereunto are added ſundry Meditations relating to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Converſion of the Soul, to which is added, A Warning to Sinners to prepare for Judgment. All Three by <hi>Nath. Vincent</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Wadſworth</hi>'s Remains: Being a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of ſome few Meditations with reſpect to the Lords Supper. Three Pious Letters when a young Student at <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Two Practical Sermons, much deſired by the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Several Sacred Poems and private Eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations. With a Preface containing ſeveral Remarkables of his Holy Life and Death, from his own Note-book, and thoſe that knew him beſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Serious Exhortation unto Self-Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Delivered in Five Sermons. on 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Theſe Two by <hi>Thomas Wadſworth,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel ſometimes at <hi>Newington-Butts, Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Old Age, tending to the Inſtruction, Caution and Comfort of Aged Perſons.</p>
            <p>Baptiſmal Bonds Renewed, being Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. By <hi>O. Heywood</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29947:46"/>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Saving Grace of God, by <hi>David Clarkſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> in Metre; cloſe and proper to the Hebrew; ſmooth and pleaſant for the Metre: To be ſung in uſual and known Tunes. Newly Tranſlated, with Amendments, and Addition of many freſh Metres. Fitted for the ready uſe, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all good Chriſtians. By <hi>Will. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> M. A. as he left it finiſhed in his life time.</p>
            <p>The difference between the Spots of the Godly and of the Wicked. Preached by Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Burroughs</hi> at <hi>Cripplegate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some Rules how to Uſe the World, ſo as not to Abuſe either that, or our ſelves. By <hi>Francis. Fuller,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Religion our True Intereſt: Or Practical Notes upon <hi>Malachi ch.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17, 18. Seaſonable for the Times. By <hi>Tho. Watſon,</hi> ſometimes Miniſter of <hi>Stephens Walbrook. London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Life and Death of <hi>Edmund Staunton</hi> D. D. To which is added, I. His Treatiſe of Chriſtian Conference. II. His Dialogue betwixt a Miniſter and a Stranger. Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Richard Mayo</hi> of <hi>Kingſton,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magna Charta Eccleſiae Univerſalis:</hi> The Grand Charter Iſſued out and Granted by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt for the Plantation of the Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:29947:47"/> Faith in all Nations. <hi>Regiſtred and Enrolled, Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. Choſen for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the enſuing Diſcourſe. By <hi>George Lawſon,</hi> Rector of <hi>More</hi> in the County of <hi>Salep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Alarme to Unconverted Sinners: In a ſerious Treatiſe; ſhewing, 1. What Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſion is not, and correcting ſome Miſtakes about it. 2. What Converſion is, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it conſiſteth. 3. The Neceſſity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. 4. The Marks of the Unconverted. 5. The Miſeries of the Unconverted. 6. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for Converſion. 7. Motives to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. Whereunto are annexed divers Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Caſes of Conſcience judiciouſly reſolved. By <hi>Joſeph Alleine</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay for the Recording of Illuſtrious Providences: Wherein, An Account is given of many Remarkable and very Memorable Events, which have happened in this laſt Age; eſpecially in <hi>New-England.</hi> By <hi>Increaſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Teacher of a Church at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Preſent to be given to Teeming Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, by their Husbands or Friends; contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scripture-Directions for Women with Child, how to prepare for the hour of Travel. Written firſt for the private uſe of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of Quality in the Weſt, and now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb facs="tcp:29947:47"/> for the common good. By <hi>John Oliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Faith of Dying <hi>Jacob.</hi> Or God's preſence with his Church, notwithſtanding the Death of his Eminent Servants. Being ſeveral Sermons from <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.21. Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the Death of Mr. <hi>Iſaac Hubbard.</hi> With the Memorials of his Life and Death. And Advice to his Young Son. By <hi>R. Gouge,</hi> Paſtor of the Church at Great <hi>Cogſhall</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
